So, let's go.
Let's get started.
I'm gonna do attendance again because DePaul is asking me to fill out that attendance survey.
So, it's nice for me to know who was actually here in the room to help with that.
So I see we have in the room here, we have Dylan and of course, this is in alphabetical
so now I'm gonna have to flip.
Oh yeah, you're a 901, that's why.
Dylan's here, Raven is here,
and then Matt is here.
And then I forgot your name.
Satyaphanath.
Can you spell the last name?
S-T?
S-T.
T-E-L-E-K.
Oh, T-E.
Yeah.
Can you pronounce your first name Satya?
Satya.
Okay.
And then Sita, that's, yeah.
Cindy, right?
I'm Julian.
Oh, Julian.
So, I just completely confused.
My last name is Che, so.
There you are.
Okay.
Cool.
I'm sorry, I apologize for that.
Over here.
My last name would be Sameer.
Sameer?
Yeah.
Are you in 901?
Yeah, you are.
Amen?
Yeah.
Yeah, and then you?
My last name is Mohammad M.
Mohammad.
Arif?
Yeah.
and why not?
My last name is Wang.
Wang?
I found you.
Oh, yeah.
And you pronounce it you-he?
You-he.
I found you-he.
OK, cool.
I'm going to work on names.
It takes a little while.
Some of you have had in class before,
so like for data structures or whatever,
so I know your faces.
Online, we have, I checked already, we have Chase.
Some folks have joined.
So we have Chase.
We have Dora.
We have Maheen.
Hang on a second.
I'm trying to make sure I got Maheen.
I found it.
And then Kush, yeah.
What's your last name, Kush?
I didn't hear you.
Can you try that again?
Brajavati.
P-R-A-J-A-P-H-E-A.
Yep, I found you.
Okay, thank you.
And is it Junaid?
Hello, I'm not sure if my name was called out.
Was that Maheen speaking?
Yes.
I got you.
Oh, okay.
Okay.
Okay, and then Junaid, there you are.
And then we have Kishan.
Okay.
Kishan, remind me your last name.
It's Cheeks.
That's right.
And then you who entered just now, can you give me your name?
Oh, I just take, I just take attendance.
Oh, okay.
What's your name?
Oh, Prithvi.
What's your last name?
Oh, Chakravarti.
Okay, I find you.
Okay.
Prithvi.
Yeah.
Okay, welcome.
Okay, that'll be the last week I do that.
If anybody comes in on the break,
I'll probably try to make an announcement.
If somebody comes in before the break,
I'll make an announcement
and just speak up and let me know you're here
so that I can give you proper credit for being here.
But I won't do that again.
So they start hounding me to make sure
that they can send you messages to say,
you signed up for the class, but you're not showing up.
So it's that kind of thing.
Okay, so a quick announcement.
So I have something that I'm doing tomorrow night
that will make it so that my normal office hours
on Wednesday will not be, I will not be at my office hours.
So I sent out a message earlier
and then I screwed up the date.
So I fixed it in a subsequent message.
So hopefully you all got email from me
saying that
that office hours for Wednesday tomorrow will move to Friday. So 6 o'clock Friday,
the regular Tuesday office hours next week will be the same before class in
this class hardly anybody ever comes to office hours so I don't really sign into
the zoom unless you send me a message saying you're coming but I am available
during the stated time so you can definitely send me a message if you plan
come um and uh you know hopefully um that will be fine for folks who need to talk to me this week
instead of tomorrow we'll just do it friday instead a little earlier 6 p.m okay so we'll
start tonight by um going through the quiz as kind of a little warm up and then we'll talk about the
homework there was one homework question that i got that i want to talk about it's really kind of a
small thing a lot of it's syntax stuff but we're learning a new language so we're dealing with
syntax that we're not used to and something that might compile might not be doing what you think
it's doing and so we need to kind of dig into that just a little bit so we'll start with a quiz
um so hopefully the quiz wasn't too hard hopefully you were able to put this
into the REPL if you were confused and learn a little bit as you went
And through the quiz, so I'm gonna get the REPL going just in case we decide to try something
out.
I don't know if that we will, but we'll just put it in here.
So first question is this code up here.
Can everybody see that okay?
So how many elements are in the result of this expression here?
So what is this expression first of all?
What kind of type is it?
List.
Somebody said list?
It's a list.
A list of what?
Integers.
Integers, right.
OK.
How do you know that's a list?
What is it that gave that away?
It doesn't say list anywhere on there.
So how do you know that?
The cons operator.
Thanks, Matt.
So this double colon here is a cons operator.
So cons is like, I think it's short for construct.
like you're constructing a list, right?
Okay, so how many elements are in that list?
Three.
Three, very good.
Did anybody think it was four?
Okay, good, even if you did
and you are embarrassed about it, that's okay,
but it's not four because this nil thing
is what we would, it's sort of like in your mind,
You want to think about that as the list terminator.
So in our old Java world, where we do data structures,
we have these nodes.
And each node points to the next node.
And if you get to the end of the list,
the last node points to null.
Well, what we're doing here is what we're
going to talk about tonight algebraic data types.
List is an algebraic data type.
There are two kinds.
It's an empty list.
there's a list with an element and a tail list.
So those are the two kinds.
We'll talk about that.
But what is this actually?
So the term I use for this is syntactic sugar.
Matt, you talked about the cons operator.
Do you know what, how I could write that differently?
The operator prepends the argument on the left
to the item on the right.
So nil being the empty list will then add three which
will then add two which will then add one.
But they're adding them to the front, which
is why you get the left to right order.
Yeah.
So what's actually happening when the way it starts evaluating
this expression is it starts with nil, the empty list.
It starts building it up.
So what actually happens is nil dot colon colon,
and then the parameter, I'm sorry,
the argument that's passed is three.
The argument is three to that first parameter.
And this whole thing is a list.
It's gonna return a list.
It's gonna evaluate to the list.
So then
this thing
Is now gonna call the cons operator again.
And so this is gonna get two.
So, to see how this is growing with parentheses,
it's like hard to follow.
And then we're gonna have one more.
And this is one.
And so the result of this thing is gonna just be,
So we can write it like this.
Like shorthand, one, two, three.
So this, you can actually type that in REPL2, it'll work.
We'll talk about why that is later.
But this is a list of three elements.
So it's not four because this is not considered an element.
It's a list of integers.
And we call reverse on it, so all that really does
is it changes this to the opposite direction,
three, two, one.
so that doesn't change anything about the number of elements.
So the answer for this one is three.
How about this next one?
It's a little different.
So we have our friend, the cons operator
that Matt pointed out.
We have this other funny little thing over here,
the three colons.
Does anybody know what the three colons is?
Does she combine lists?
Yeah, combine, append,
okay, concatenate,
like is another way to think about it.
So what you're actually doing is you're taking two lists,
and you're squishing together into one list.
Right? So how many elements in the result here?
Six, very good.
Okay.
This next one might throw you through me because I went too fast when I did the quiz.
I didn't read the full question.
So how many elements are there in this result here?
And you have to now count all of the elements in the result, not just those in the top of
the list.
So the easy thing to do is to say, well, I have a list of two things.
So it's two.
Except inside this list, there are nested lists, right?
So each of those nested lists has three and three, and so the answer is eight.
You can all add today.
Okay.
So I did not pay attention when I did the quiz, and I got 90% last night when I did it.
I'm not my computer, maybe I should look at my screen and not there.
All right.
Next one.
So here we have an expression list of list, and there's these two lists.
This is similar to what we've been looking at.
And now it's asking which of the following expressions creates the same list so
the list above.
So, what do we think the answer is?
First, second, third, or fourth, A, B, C, D maybe you'll call it.
.
Fourth. Somebody said four.
A?
Sorry?
A.
A, the first one?
So you think it's the first one.
Any other opinions?
Okay. I'm going to agree with you.
It is A.
So how can we, if we're looking at this question, how can we test this out?
Just copy and paste in the REPL.
Put in the REPL. Right, so I'm gonna try each one. So let's let's start with the fourth one because somebody said that, so let's start with that.
If I paste that in there, what do I get?
I get this funny looking thing.
So the type here is a list of, and then it's got this funny expression in here. This is, um, an OR, it's also called a SUM type.
What this means is the elements of the list are either int or lists of int.
So what's happening here is the type inference engine in compiler is figuring out what the type of that expression is and it's telling you.
You gave me a list that has this stuff in it, and this is the type.
So that is not, if we compare that with this list of lists that we had,
it's not the same thing.
So let's take a look.
For that we get a list of list of int.
So the types here do not match.
And in fact, the structure of the list don't match.
The data doesn't match.
So if we take the first one and paste that in.
For that we get a list of list of int.
And you see that these two match up.
The data matches up as well as the types match up.
Okay, so this is how when you're studying, doing the quiz,
you should definitely, if you're not sure, don't get it wrong,
try it, validate your assumption, right?
But then make sure if you didn't get it right the first time,
like when you were thinking about it,
like make sure when you thought about it
and the answer you thought it was,
then you got a different answer.
Make sure you understand why.
And then make sure you take notes or write that down and study that, right?
because this stuff is going to keep coming back up.
And the more we iterate, the more we practice, the more we learn.
All right, so now we have this expression, we have, what is this called?
What kind of thing is this?
Tuple.
It's a tuple, right?
Also known as, in this case it's a three-tuple because it has three elements.
And what is that, what are the types that are contained in the tuple?
An int, right, okay.
So, which answer is it?
You said it aloud, so it's the third one, right?
Why is it not a list of string?
And an int?
It's not the list.
It's not a list.
Very good, right?
I mean, you can see here, you just have this forens.
this syntax means you have a tuple right. Whenever you see the parents you have a tuple.
Okay, so string string int.
Okay, what about this list of one, two, three, four?
It's a list of int. Couldn't be more simpler than that. It's not a list of strings because
these aren't string expressions, these are its. It's not a list of tuples because
inside the list you don't have tuples. A list of tuples would look more like, let's
see, that's got four tuples, so this would be blue. We would have a list of
of 1, 2, 3, 4 but this 1, 2, 3, 4 has this extra layer of parentheses.
So that syntax would imply something different, imply a different meaning.
So that's how you would get that one, but that's not the one we have.
Okay.
Now we have a list of these things.
So similar to before, we have what inside the list?
All tuples.
Tuples.
There are two tuples this time because they each have two elements.
The tuple types are int and string.
And so what we have is a list of tuples of int string.
So I think the answer is the first one.
Okay.
Now we have a list of something inside.
And the things inside, what do those look like?
We've talked about those things before.
Those are lists.
Right?
Lists of what?
Integers.
And so we have which of these types is it going to be?
Okay.
Four.
The last one.
I agree with that.
So you have a list event, a list event, a list event, and each of these lists is contained
within this outer list, so you have a list of list events.
All right.
So that's that.
So what is the result of evaluating this Scala expression?
Any idea?
Four.
Okay, so we have a four.
So talk us through why you got four.
This first one is x plus x.
And let's use two.
Two multiplied two.
Okay.
So let's kind of break it down.
So in here, inside this brace or these two braces, we're assigning...
First, we're actually evaluating three expressions.
We're not executing statements here.
We're evaluating expressions.
There's a lecture tonight, topic tonight on statements versus expressions.
So these are three different expressions and they're separated by the semicolon.
And so in Scala, the value of this expression is the last expression in the sequence.
So we start with this expression.
We have a var x.
We set it equal to 1.
And then we update it by incrementing it by 1.
So now our x is now equal to 2.
And then the final expression evaluates that variable.
And we get 2.
So the whole value of this thing, when you evaluate that expression, you get 2.
Now over here we have another one of these so we're going to multiply that. We're going to take 2 multiplied by whatever the
result of this expression is. Now inside here we have a completely different x. Does everybody understand why?
Because it's inside this parentheses. So here we have a new x, it's a var,
so we set it equal to 1. And then we update it again by incrementing so now we're equal to 2.
two and then we evaluate this last expression x, which is two, so we end up with two times
two and so that would yield...the entire thing would evaluate to four.
So if you think this is elementary, just wait, we're gonna go deep next.
This is why I said it's a warm up.
Now last question.
So we have this scalar function definition.
The question asks, this definition,
what is the result of evaluating this expression f of 5?
15.
Somebody says 15.
I agree.
Let's talk about why though.
So just let's break it down.
So we have f of 5.
And if we want to think about f of 5,
what happens when we call f of 5?
Well, x is going to be 5, so x is not going to be equal to 0.
So we're going to hit this else.
And then we'll say 5 plus f of 4.
So this will expand.
we can expand this to 5 plus F of 4. Okay, so now we're going to keep going. 5 plus,
and now we've got, we're going to now evaluate this piece. So this is 4 plus F of 3. Everybody
see that? Okay, now we again have 5 plus 4 plus 3 plus F of 2. And keep going.
f of 1 and then we're going to finally
oops we need 1 plus that's not the eraser here it looked like my power adapter and my eraser
This is the same, plus 1 plus f of 0.
And actually, it would help if I put the parentheses in, right?
So for here, I'm going to.
And we're going to, and I'm doing this for a reason, because they're going to roll up.
Let me have, same deal.
Okay, so we'll get all the way down here.
F of 0, we call F of 0.
Well, this time, X is going to be equal to 0.
So the whole thing just evaluates to 0.
So then this becomes 0, and then we'll do this addition to get 1 plus 0.
And then that'll be 1.
I'm not going to write it all out because I ran out of board space.
I wrote kind of big, but you can kind of visualize in your mind.
So if you're going to write out the whole evaluation,
this is what you would do.
This would be 0, 1 plus 0.
You would write the whole line again.
That's a lot to write, so we're not going to do it.
But 1 plus 0 is 1, so we'll then add 2 to it.
So it'll roll up like this as the recursion exits.
So if you add all this up, you get 50.
So that was a nice warm-up.
Let's see if we got them all right.
I'm pretty sure we did and 10 out of 10, cool.
There are no stupid questions on this stuff.
If you don't understand the syntax, you don't know what you're doing.
I'm in the middle of learning Rust right now, and sometimes I'm like what the heck,
why is the compiler giving me this error?
Hopefully, what classes like this will help you to do is to figure out how to get
the answers you can think about it, okay?
So, please ask questions, that's what we're here for.
So any questions on the quiz?
Everybody good?
Everybody got 100, right?
No, I've got the same one that you got wrong.
Oh, so it's easy to forget to read carefully.
Yeah, I do that too.
Human.
All right.
So great.
So now let's talk about the homework.
I don't know if there were specific questions, but I do wanna cover the third one first.
This was the one on the print matrix.
So here in my IntelliJ window, I had a student come to me and was confused about why they were getting.
I didn't implement all of these here, so I just took that code and put it in here.
So if we look at the code for exercise three, there it is.
So this is the one where we're calling print, we're passing an array of arrays of hits,
and we're turning it into a string.
And this would be a string that we can print out.
And so the directions say, well, if you get a pound, that's when you have a one, and then
the space is when you have the zero. I guess it's nonzero is pound 0 is one okay.
So we gave you a Java implementation because you're all familiar with Java so
hopefully you can look at the Java and try to figure out how to write it in
Scala. So what we got here is this student decided to use a StringBuilder.
So as a person who has worked with Java before,
and I said, everything in Java is available in Scala,
you can use this string builder, just like before.
Just like you did in Java, just like the Java code does.
And that is how you do it in Java.
You always have to use a string builder
because strings are immutable,
you can't just change strings.
All right, so here we have this expression here,
this for do, and I'm going to not call it a loop
because it's technically a for comprehension.
But we'll talk about that when we do functional programming.
We'll talk about what that means.
But what we have here is we're going and we're saying, okay,
for each row and then for each cell in each row,
we're going to examine the cell to see if it's zero.
And if it's not zero, we're going to do the pound
and if it is zero, we're going to do the space.
And then we add this append and then at the end,
we add this other append for a new line.
So we have these new lines coming in.
And then we need to call results a two string,
and this is a pretty standard job.
Okay, so.
The test is failing
because, and actually we can go to the code.
So, an empty array, so this would be the empty outer array
should just be an empty string.
There should be no new line characters.
So we've got some sort of off by one error.
Okay, so if we look at the Java code,
notice that we have two nested fours.
So if we take that and think about it in Scala terms,
we actually could write it with two for loops, right?
So we could say, or four comprehensions.
So we could, instead of this, so this worked, right?
is compiled, right?
But this is actually not what you want.
So what we actually want is we want for do.
And then inside, we have another for do.
And let's see.
I think in here, do we need, let me check the Java.
So in Java, we only have one Append new line, right?
In the Java code, so we would change this
to just have one, and the one that we have
is outside the inner four, so it's in the outer four,
but outside the inner four.
So we're gonna then take this out,
Oops, pressing the wrong button.
So if we line this up, that should be right.
And then we call result.txt string.
So let's see if that fixes the problem.
I hope so.
I didn't test this out.
Running the tests again.
and it can be a little slow.
And now it doesn't work at all.
Oh no, it does work, look.
The only ones that fail are one, two, four, five, six,
so it looks like exercise three tests succeeded.
So the key here was that, to do it this way,
you needed to copy the Java code literally
and transcribe it to Scala, right, with a nested force.
Now, what the student did, compiled,
And it could work.
But you might have to add extra if checks everywhere
to see whether you're adding a new line.
And then it gets messy.
We will get into, when we do functional programming,
how these relate to a function call map.
We're not really going to cover that yet.
But in Scala, every time we have a for,
we either have a for each or a map.
So in this case, because it's for do, we have for each.
If we used yield here, and if you've done your reading
or looked at the book, you'll see there's a for yield version.
That converts to a map function.
We'll talk about that when we get to functional programming.
So for now, this is an acceptable way to do this,
by using the for do this way.
The solution I have actually has a different way to do it.
And I want to share that with you, just because it is interesting.
I think it was exercise three, print it's called.
So here, it did something different.
Maybe I did something.
So still, in this case, we have two fours, right?
So two four expressions.
But notice instead of do, we have yield, okay?
So this is gonna be the one that converts to a map function that we'll study later.
And actually what's happening is it's like taking each row of the matrix,
and so each of these arrays and then it's mapping a function over that, okay?
And then this whole business inside here is that function.
And now we have another nested one of these, right?
And so, here it calls micstring which is a function on arrays.
So this is actually preserving the arrays, the outer array structure.
And then at the end we add a new line at the very end and call make string again.
So this is a way to do it too.
If you've stumbled on that in your reading or whatever, that's perfectly fine.
You're just getting a little bit ahead of us.
So don't worry about that for now.
We'll talk about this, I think it's next week or the week after.
Okay, I just wanted to cover that because the question came up.
Any questions about this one?
Yeah, Raven.
So you mentioned the for comprehension.
Is that different than the nested expression?
So a for comprehension is simply some sort of for,
it's either gonna be for something, and then do,
something and then do or for and then yield.
Either of those is, technically that's a for comprehension.
I can't remember if actually it's only this one,
I can't remember that's the subtle technical detail.
But these are four expressions.
But nested expressions are something different.
Like nested expressions are,
because we have two of these,
Those are nested.
Okay.
But that's what that means.
Good question.
All right, anything else on this one?
Anything on other homework questions?
Nobody ever asks the homework and then I get lazy and I don't look at it.
And then I come to class and I don't know.
So I'm trying to look at it.
So if you wanna catch me, see now I just challenged my, see I just said that to you all.
And now if you want to catch me, make sure...
if you want to make sure I do my homework,
come with a question.
All right, so anything else on this stuff?
Good.
Oh, go ahead.
Sorry, one more question.
For like a standard 2D or 3D or whatever array,
I saw a couple ways to do it, but they have the dimension.
Is that the standard way?
Yeah.
Or would you do like the array of an array?
You can do that.
So this is what you're talking about, array of dim.
This line here.
Yes.
So what this is saying is.
Actually, let's look at of dim.
Let's just see what it looks like.
So in this case, there's a whole bunch of fun little
scholar syntax here,
which might throw you off because you're not familiar with looking.
I know whenever I look at new code or a new language,
when I don't understand the syntax,
my eyes go, I can't read it because I don't know what it means.
So you can ignore this for now.
But , is saying this is my first dimension,
this is my second dimension,
so it's going to actually do this.
So under the covers,
it's doing what you're talking about.
So if you wanted to do this manually, it'd be fine.
This is just a little easier because the arrays object that we're in, oh sorry, the array object that we're in here, this comes with Scala, right?
So the reason I throw this up in IntelliJ is for two reasons.
One, I use IntelliJ and I know how to get around it.
And two, like it gets me into the Scala library so I can like demonstrate or show you like what it's actually doing.
So if you want to type this out yourself, you can.
You can instantiate arrays.
just like you would have to do in Java, perhaps.
So it doesn't matter which way you do it.
This is just a little easier
because it provides this little utility method for you to call
and you don't have to have all that boilerplate there.
Great question.
Other questions?
Okay.
Great.
well then, we will go ahead and tackle some new material tonight.
So we're going to start with this idea about contracts and unit tests.
So we did some unit tests in the code.
So actually, in your homework, you will see that these tests.
There's this create.
I'm in the wrong file.
That's why I had to go down and test.
Yeah, these tests are declared with this property.
And what this is actually doing is it's showing
of these properties are valid, right.
So, these are unit tests that I give you in your homework
and generally you're never gonna change the unit tests
unless I tell you to, which I don't think I ever do.
So, now we're gonna kinda think about software code,
how do we know that it's correct?
So, we're thinking kind of at this high level.
So, let's say I tell ChatGPT or Claude
to implement an iterative Skeleth 3 program
that computes the factorial of a number.
So there's an answer, so Claude comes up with that.
So what do we got?
We have factorial n, it takes an int, returns an int.
It uses this mutable storage result,
and then it does this thing that looks like a for loop,
but we call it in this class,
we call this a for expression, right?
So we have 1, 2, n, and that's inclusive, and
then we're going to just do this multiply.
Notice it's not 0.
What happens if we were to do 0?
What if Claude gave you 0 there?
Would it work?
The whole thing would become 0.
The whole thing becomes 0, Matt, right.
Tell us why.
Do you end up multiplying by 0?
Right.
So you're always gonna end up with zero here
and you'll never, so multiplicative identity is one,
additive identity is zero.
We're not adding, we're multiplying.
So we need to start with one
in order to get the proper definition of a factorial.
However, Claude has been known to screw that up.
Like I was working with Claude last week
and I said, fix this code.
And it went and fixed the code except it broke the code.
But it insisted it was right.
And I told it, no, that is not what I want.
I want you to fix this, and then it tried to change the unit test on me.
And I said, no, the unit test is correct.
So you've got to know what you're doing when you're dealing with these tools.
And actually, I like to tell students this now, like as I said this maybe last week,
but as like these AI tools start to become more and more ubiquitous around us,
we're going to have to learn how to work with them.
And if you learn how to work with them and be smarter than them, then you will have a job.
And if you let it do your work and screw everything up, then you'll get fired and
Claude will get a bad name too. So as a software engineer at this stage of my
career with all these AI things coming out, the key is to learn how to use them.
And that means playing around and experimenting. And that's totally fine.
Like I said, you can use it to learn in this class, but eventually I'll put a
graph up that'll show you. There's always a cluster of students who get really
high grades on the study guides and get really low grades on the exams. That
usually tells me what's going on here. I know you're not doing the work that you
need to do to actually learn the material. Alright so we have this code. So how do
we use factorial? That's one question. We have another question. Is the code
correct? How can we convince ourselves whether the code is correct? So those are those are our
questions right? So whenever working with code whether it's like me 30 years ago before ai-tools
or now that question comes to mind how do I know that this code that I have is correct?
So we're going to talk about how we can build trust in. I have auto-generated code in friends.
We're gonna talk about unit tests and talk about contracts.
So unit tests, in their simplest form, provide sample inputs and
test expected outputs of code in isolation.
So in our unit test, we have expected behavior.
We can look at the unit test and we can see what the test asserts, right?
I don't know if you've taken any software engineering classes, but
but I think if you take software engineering classes,
you will have to do some unit testing in there.
If you took my data structures to class,
in grad class last spring,
I think it was already a year ago.
Yeah, they started making me teach this one which I don't mind
because I think about this stuff all the time.
I asked you to make sure you wrote the test unit tests.
I don't go into a lot of like what that is,
but you have to test your code.
So unit tests, they specify expected behavior,
but they're also documentation.
I don't know how many times I have been working with a software library and said, you know what?
I don't know how to use this library.
But you know what?
I know it's well tested because I trust the open source community that my company is using this library.
And we've all kind of decided this is something that is good and useful.
So I'm going to go pull the source code for that library.
And I'm going to go find the unit test where this particular area of the library is exercised in the test.
and then that will provide me documentation on how to use it.
Sometimes the documentation isn't so good.
Software engineers don't always write good documentation.
I've been on teams where they've actually asked me
to just do all their documentation and I said no.
I did not go into this field to write documentation for software.
We have technical writers for that.
My job is to write code and once in a while I'll write something
because I need to document what I've done and share it with coworkers.
But going into the unit test can help you to see
what you need to understand about the code that you're working with. So it might
tell you how to initialize and use code, what to expect as a result on legal
inputs, and what to expect as an exception on a legal input. And so these
things, these unit tests, prevent quality regression. I remember when I was a newly
minted software engineer. Regression testing was something that I was like,
I was like, what's a regression test? Well, regression testing is when you test to
make sure that some code change didn't make you go backwards,
regress, do something that would break the code system.
So in Scala tests, this is a little different
than the way your homework does it.
This is using Scala tests.
And on the right here, we have this sort of expression,
this is a flat spec because there are different ways
to express unit tests but this is sort of a flat way to express it.
So you're saying that the factorial function should compute zero factorial
correctly. So if I call factorial zero I should get one. A lot of times we
write these tests before we actually write the code. That's called test driven
development. I learned that on a job interview. I was like out of school in
10 years and I was like actually out of my master's program about three years. I
went on a job interview and they didn't hire me because I didn't know how to do
test-driven development because the place I worked at wasn't doing it.
Right? But you can write all these tests first, and then you implement the code
and make sure that the tests all pass. And with your homework, that's what you're
getting. You're getting a suite of unit tests that fail. And then you're gonna
execute those and start to implement your homework, and then you'll start to see
the test go green. Right? That's the whole. So one factorial should be one, three
factorials should be 6, and you can express these. These are, we sometimes
call these example-based tests, so you're providing specific examples. So we
have these matchers, should matchers, that express the expected results. But this
is kind of limited because it only can let you express a finite number of
examples, right? I mean I could write forever and ever, I could have Claude
write forever and never finish because there's an infinite number of examples.
So this has limited utility. However that doesn't mean it has no utility.
Sometimes you have specific examples. Oftentimes I'll get like something in
production that fails and then I'm like okay I'm gonna write a specific test for
that and I'm gonna assert in my code base that that particular thing should
always, input should always produce that particular output even three- three
years from now and I changed the library five times.
So sometimes we throw those in.
Okay, now we have this other idea, contracts.
So contracts are formal and verifiable interface specifications, so we have preconditions,
post conditions, and invariance.
So preconditions are expectations that the client needs to honor.
Post-conditions are guaranteed by the software that you're executing.
And then invariance are maintained.
We talked about loop invariance when I teach data structures.
Every time the loop iterates, there's something true about the loop.
We have the notion of class invariance in object-oriented programming,
where something is true about the class every time.
So this is, you don't have to worry about this so much,
this is because these slides originated
from someone who likes to do research in computer science.
So these are gonna be presented this way.
These are Horre triples, I guess, they're called.
Tony Horre is a computer scientist from England.
I don't know if he's still with us,
His name popped up 35 years ago when I was in undergrad.
And there is a talk I link somewhere where I think
he talks about he invented Null.
And Null is his least favorite invention,
because it screws up cost.
At that time, like, 17 years ago, he was saying that it
was cost over $1 billion.
That seems so low today.
$1 billion seems so low today with all the things
here in the news about the billions of dollars and all that.
Anyway, modal logic.
This is how you express it, but what does it mean?
This is what it looks like in code.
So in Scala code, if I have C, require P.
So that's my, I'm requiring this precondition,
and then ensuring Q, this is my postcondition.
And you'll see in some of the code we have,
this ensuring stuff in some of our homework.
Theorem proving, this actually shows,
this is different than unit testing.
So theorem proving shows correctness mathematically
for all possible inputs.
There are things called theorem provers.
And I think in 535 they actually do something with that.
know if they're teaching 535 anymore. I've heard that there are a lot of students who want to take
535, it's formal semantics of programming languages. I took it when I was here.
And I came in like, came and attended some classes a few years after I graduated, and
professor Riley had changed up the course, and he was using a theorem prover in the course,
and that was not something we had back when I was taking the class the first time.
There's another way to do verification called model checking. That's going to show correctness
for finite-length executions. This is somewhat informational. You don't have to memorize this.
And then runtime verification checks contracts while executing the software.
So every time it's called, it's going to check something. So in our insuring clauses and
some of our homework assignments, that's runtime verification. It's actually checking the results
as you go. So contracts and Scala, you'll see we'll have this insuring business here.
And actually I can jump over to do we have any insuring in the last homework?
I can't remember.
No we don't.
You'll start to see it in the second homework.
I think there was a couple insurings in the homework.
You know what I was doing?
Thanks Matt.
I was looking in the test file but I should have probably looked it here.
Thanks for pointing that out.
Yeah there it is.
So here you had to implement board and then I was insuring.
The reason I wanted to come over here actually is I can like, oh, what is it, I can't find
the declaration.
Is it in there?
No.
Okay.
Well, somewhere insuring is gonna take the result and look at the result and do something,
so there's some definition, it takes a function.
So this is taking the result, whatever this expression yields,
whatever type that yields, it takes the result of that type,
and it does something, you would implement that.
And this is actually, this syntax here is a function.
So you have a function with a parameter and then it executes that.
And then the implementation of ensuring is gonna actually execute this as a side effect,
and if it fails, it'll throw exception.
And if not, if it doesn't fail, then it will return the result that got that it passed in hearing.
And then earlier, the first time I taught the course, I think it was an older version of Scala,
and I think this was implemented within the Hallmark itself and not implemented,
like it's implemented somewhere in the library.
In this version, Scala will read, I think.
But I don't use this in my work life, like this insuring business.
This was new to me when I started teaching this class.
Because this would actually slow things down.
So runtime checking adds computational overhead.
But this contract, this part here, can be an alternate implementation.
So how useful is it to have the exact same code over here?
very useful in my opinion.
So if we look at this code,
this code here looks just like this code here.
So maybe we should change the implementation to do it,
to compute it a different way.
So here's an alternative solution where we do this,
where we actually do some kind of recursion here, right?
We can compute factorial using recursion.
So we do it differently.
So this actually comes up in my own, not so much this century,
but in my own work.
I importing some logic out of some services,
some software services, and moving into a common library
because they're going to be shared across different services
now.
And what I did was actually took the old code that
was actually computing a hash of fields.
And I took that code and I put it into my library in the test area.
And I said, for every test that I run,
I'm going to compute some hash of the fields of my business domain object.
And then I'm going to execute the legacy code,
which is maybe implemented differently than the prepared results.
So it's the same idea.
So I do use this.
In my work life, though, I don't do this.
I actually do something called property-based testing where you actually generate arbitrary examples like 100 or 1,000.
I actually did 10,000 in the thing I'm working on.
And I run this as part of the build so it doesn't run at runtime in production.
It runs when I build the software so that I can catch bugs early.
That's typically how, out in the field, how we do things.
We don't want our actual software systems to be impacted by doing all this runtime verification.
You still have to validate inputs and respond to errors, that's kind of a different concept.
So here's the summary.
So unit tests, we're executing code with some inputs and test for expected outputs.
This is like what we have in our homework in those test files that you don't change.
Game of life tests this last time.
This will, these tests will document behavior and expectations and there'll be a finite
number of tests.
So this is a downside.
That's why this is a minus here.
And it's best for regression testing.
Contracts, we are, express input assumptions and output guarantees.
So this will show correctness for all possible inputs and executions, but
the downside is there's a lot of computational overhead, extra effort.
This is best for correctness, critical applications.
I've never seen these used in the field.
Maybe if I were writing something for the Artemis mission or
something, there would probably have to be a whole bunch of like error handling.
and you don't want the astronauts to die.
So they have to do something to make sure
that any errors that are encountered or dealt with,
that is a, I've never worked on that kind of code.
I've always worked on web services for business.
If you're working on code for medical devices,
perhaps that would be more important.
That's just kind of some background on how we verify,
how we ensure, how we convince ourselves
code is correct. Okay so that gives you some background on what you're going to
see in the homework going forward. Some of what you've already seen in the homework.
Now we're going to dive into some more Scala specific. So we're going to talk about
syntax and what it means with Scala language. So we'll talk about a couple
A couple different concepts in Scala pattern matching, and classes.
And then we'll talk about algebraic data types.
So, as I said last week, in data structures we have abstract data types.
Those are different than what we're gonna talk about algebraic data types.
I think we talked a little bit about them last week, but
we'll dig a little bit more next week.
Start with pattern.
So for this set of slides,
we're gonna be thinking about how do we decompose and
process complex nested data structures.
We're gonna look at matched expressions and
cases in the sky pattern matching.
And we're gonna express functions in pattern matching so
we'll see what this all means.
So here I'm telling Claude again or chat GPT in Scala implement a method that takes at least
a list of at least three numbers and returns it with the first three numbers sorted in ascending order.
Okay so we need a contract for checking the first three elements.
So here we have this function with this implementation.
It's got this require, right?
That's checking the precondition, then it's got the implementation and
then it returns something then it has this insuring part.
And this is a function that's going to take the result and
it's going to check that it actually did what it was supposed to do.
So we can do it this way.
This is the old fashioned index access.
Knowing what we know about lists, is this the most efficient way?
No.
I see nos.
Okay, so why?
What if the requirements were like the first 100,000 numbers?
Or, well, 100,000 isn't going to matter on our hardware.
But what if it was like a million?
Ten million?
A hundred million?
First of all, I would have to write all that, right?
Or I'd have to write some for in here or something like that.
But what happens when I do this?
We know that these lists are these cons cells or nil.
So if I have a cons cell and I want one millionth element,
how do I get to it?
Think about data structures. Think about link lists.
You've got to traverse the entire thing.
you got to traverse the entire map.
So this may not be the most efficient.
Now for this little three element thing, it doesn't matter, right?
You can but each time it's gonna walk through this list, right?
It's gonna walk zero steps, one step, and two steps.
But it's gonna repeat itself and walk where it's already walking.
And then at the bottom, okay, so once it gets these, then it says, okay,
the first element must be less than or equal to second element.
The second element must be less than or equal to the third element.
So both of these has to be true, okay?
And so, this thing has to return a Boolean, this function.
This function takes the result and returns a Boolean.
That's pretty much going to be standard,
and ensuring has to return a Boolean too.
I didn't say that before.
Here's another way to do it.
So we talked last week about list projections.
List projections are those head and tail methods.
So here what I'm doing is I'm saying,
OK, x1 is going to get result.head,
x2 is going to get result.tail.head, and x3 is going to get result.tail.tail.head.
This is actually the same kind of thing.
We're just repeating ourselves, right?
Result, tail, head, tail, tail, head.
We're blocking where we blocked before.
So here is pattern matching.
Looks like two things popped up.
All right, so what we got?
Yeah.
So you can write it this way.
Where you get the result is a list of ints, and
then you decompose this list by doing this pattern matching thing.
Where you actually say, I'm gonna take the result, and
I'm gonna say, I'm gonna bind the first element of the list to x1.
And the second element of the list to x2 and the third element of the list to x3.
So there is, on the list, there's a function, you can look it up in your text called
unapply, in Scala we have apply and unapply.
We'll talk about apply more later, unapply is actually gonna do the work to decompose this.
So this is the same type of thing here where it's saying, well, all right,
x1 has to be less than x2 and x2 has to be less than x3.
and S3 .
So, the other way you could do this is you can dispense with this part,
you don't have to do this part, and you can use this as a case, expression,
case, and then this does the same thing.
It decomposes the list.
So there's this implied parameter here.
And this is pretty standard scholar syntax for this.
So you can do it this way.
So this is an example, on that side of the slide, an example of pattern matching because
you've matched a pattern.
Now what happens if the pattern doesn't match?
What if it's an empty list?
I'm going to get some kind of an error.
And actually that's what you want because you want it to throw some kind of error if
it doesn't work.
I guess you want it to return false or throw an error.
But if you throw an error in, then you've got a problem.
I think if you return false here, the code calling insuring,
this insuring function will actually throw an assumption,
I think.
So pattern matching.
It branches and binds.
It does both of these things.
So what does that mean?
Well, here's decompensi- so let's look at this example
first, decomposition index axis. So we have here we have a tufl, p, it has an int and
an int and we're saying if we got null for p, we'll for a match error. We didn't match
anything. Otherwise, we can access the tuple and get the 0th element, or we could say the
first element but you referenced it this way with 0, and then get the first element, the
element, so x and y. And then add x and y and return that. So remember the last expression
is whatever that evaluates to is the return value, and that's an 8. You don't have to
say return. It's valid. But you generally don't use the word return. Although I did
get dinked on an interview, a job interview once, for not writing the word return. Because
They were doing a whole different kind of problem
that I normally work with where they needed the code
to execute super efficiently.
I used to do that when I worked at a financial exchange.
I don't do that anymore.
So I was like, yeah, I don't think that.
So we can do that same thing with pattern matching.
So if we take this P, which is the same input.
a tuple with two elements, int and int, and we say p match, and then we can deconstruct
that tuple and bind each element to variables of our choosing.
So here we have x and y, so we're binding to x and binding to y, and then we're taking
that and we're yielding x plus y.
And this is actually a function.
So you can actually write, anywhere in Scala where you can have like this kind of thing,
you can actually write the types here too.
So sometimes, this is a simple one, so I don't need to, but if I, sometimes I'm dealing with,
you can go up to, I think it's like 24 tuples, or 22 tuples, I can't remember.
Scala supports like up to 22 elements in tuples, and then if you have something that big, I
actually had this.
I was looking at code and my eyes were popping out of my head and I was like I don't know
what I'm dealing with.
So I'm going to tell IntelliJ, tell me what these types are.
And I can right click and say, annotate the type.
It's a really wonderful feature that's why I use IntelliJ.
I'm sure BS Code has it.
So every time you see this case, arms, arrow,
this is the double equal, the equal sign arrow,
and then somebody, that's this pattern here, that's a function.
It's actually a function.
So let's do this where we're printing the first element
of the list.
So this is called print head.
We get access list.
And we're going to use this if else here.
This is the way that we usually think about it
when we're dealing with some of the languages like Java, C,
Python maybe, I think Python might have pattern matching.
I'm not sure I don't do Python, so don't quote me on any of that.
But we're checking the list, if it's empty, nil,
then we'll return the string list is empty.
I'm assuming some calling code is printing that string or something.
Otherwise, we'll use list projections here, we'll get the head, and
we'll get the tail, and we'll say, list is not empty, the head is y.
That's it, we're just printing the head and we're done.
So we can do this with decomposition is the same here,
but we're doing pattern matching instead of if else.
So we're saying xs, so we're taking this thing.
We have this match keyword and we say, all right, if I got a new,
we're gonna return the string list is empty.
And if I got something and something else here.
So I got a head with some tail and I don't actually care because I never actually use
it.
We'll talk about that in a second.
I'm gonna produce this string.
By the way this part here where you see s and quotes and then this dollar y it's actually
splicing and it's called string interpolation in Scala but it's actually taking this y
and splicing it in.
So it's converting this to a string and then building this string by splicing that.
So under the covers it's doing something like with a string buffer, probably, but
we don't, we don't care.
That's what this syntax means.
When you see s before the, the quotes, that's what, what it's doing.
And usually you would use that when you have some kind of dollar.
If you have, where you're interpolating some variable,
when you have something more complex where you wanna,
if you had y that wasn't an int but you wanted to access a field.
You can then put curly braces after the dollar sign and then the expression and
then another curly brace there, so that would work too.
So it's string interpolation.
So if we do this, we can actually omit unnecessary variables and types.
So is that.
So here, over here we have to do this here.
So we would leave out this access dot tail, because we don't need it, right?
We're never using it, so we can just eliminate that.
How that works with pattern matching?
Well, we use y, cuz we wanna bind to some variable that we're
gonna use here in the string, and we're interpolating into the string.
And then this tail, we don't care what it is.
So we just use this underscore so it doesn't bind to anything.
It's just a placeholder.
So this wildcard operator means don't care.
So we have nested patterns, so patterns
can include other patterns.
So if we're printing the first tuple of a singleton list,
Or we're going to print the first tuple of a singleton list.
Otherwise, we're going to print the second int.
So, singleton list means there's one element, right?
So, if I have one element, so that's what this case here is,
I'm going to say, I'm going to print my one element.
We have to pattern match with this nil here because that's empty.
Notice we also have to include the case for empty list.
You'll get an error if you try to, if you exclude a case.
If there's ever any inputs that might not match, you'll get some kind of error.
So here you could have an empty list.
Notice, by the way, our type of the elements held by the list are these tuples, right?
So they have an int and a string.
So if I get an empty list, I say list is empty.
I return that.
If I have a singleton list, that's this here.
I'm going to interpolate the exit here.
List has one element.
And otherwise, the next thing I'm going to do is I'm going to do this.
I'm gonna say, okay, I don't care and I got a tuple of I care about the first
element that int is gonna get bound to x but the string I don't care so I use the
underscore and then anything after here. This could be a nil, it could be another
list. I don't care. So we're destructuring this list and we're taking just in the
second element, we're taking the first element of the tuple in that second
element of the list. That makes sense. And then printing that out or returning the string.
So if I call on- I have my zs, there's my list. And I call f. I'm gonna get back 2
because it's gonna match this case here and the 2 is going to bind to x and
it's gonna give me the string back.
Excuse me?
Yes?
Why would you need a nil for the second one?
The third one?
Why would I need a what?
Yeah.
A nil?
Why don't I need a nil?
I mean, why would you-
Oh, this, you mean the second one.
The third one.
Oh, the third one.
Yeah, the third one doesn't have-
Doesn't have nil?
Yeah.
Yeah, because it could be nil, might not be nil.
I don't care.
It could be two elements in the list with a nil as the tail or it could be more than
two elements with some con cell here but I don't care so I'm not binding to any.
So what happens if we add a nil on the end?
I guess it's equals to each other?
If you add a nil there, that is not equal to this expression.
So, nil is the like, we add it at end not to replace it.
Where are you adding the nil, here?
No, no, no.
The end.
Yeah.
You're sticking nil on the end of the case expression, not replacing the underscore.
Oh, oh, oh.
Yeah, no, that doesn't matter.
It doesn't matter.
Yeah.
It doesn't matter but what you do need to know is that it will, when it executes this
code, it matches the first thing.
So sometimes, if you switch the order of things, it might matter.
In this case, I don't think it would.
You don't have to put the nil first.
Thank you for the clarification.
I thought you were trying to ask me about putting nil here.
And that's a separate question.
And if you did that, you would need yet another, you need more cases, right?
Because if you have something other than it.
So that's a different thing.
So it's gonna match in order.
And if you move this one here, I think it'll try each one, if you had a nil, it would fail,
it would fail.
And if you move this to the last case, it would then match that, and it should be okay.
So in this case it doesn't matter.
Okay, so now we're going to try implementing
some list operations by pattern match.
Raise this and try it out.
All right, so if we try to do is empty,
So if we have isEmpty, what is that going to return?
Boolean.
Boolean?
You can leave that off because the compiler would try to interpret,
inference would try to use inference to figure out the type.
We're going to need an equal sign to begin the body of the method.
So how would we use pattern matching?
I guess we would have to, let's use,
I don't remember if we have the parameters, so we'll just say.
We have a list of int.
and we're gonna return Boolean,
and spell, equals, okay, so what are we gonna do?
We're gonna take Xs, and we're gonna do what?
Match.
I know this is new to you.
So what do we have here?
Case.
All right, what case do you wanna do?
Is nil?
No.
So what we're doing is empty.
So if we have nil, that is by definition the empty list.
So we return true true true true.
And then, what do we want to do here?
.
Just plain old underscore.
I like that.
Why did you say underscore?
It could be anything.
Could be anything.
Don't care.
Anything other than 0.
Match this and we return false.
So there you go.
Yeah.
It would be considered poor practice to just instead of writing the case underscore false
just having false as the last expression in the body?
Since it's gonna return here?
Just having false at the end since it's gonna return whatever the last evaluation is.
Oh like under it.
Kind of like simulating an early return.
So I think what you mean is,
I'm gonna do what Matt is suggesting in red.
Instead of this all together right?
Yeah.
And just put the false here?
Yeah, is that considered like poor form in Scholar?
Yes, so yes, it's bad, because what will happen is
this match expression will fail to match on this case.
And so it'll give you a match error,
probably throw an error.
Okay, so it doesn't just fall through
if you don't put in like a default case here or something?
Nope, you have to include all the possible cases,
so you have to have some expression for each possible case.
Can you go back a slide?
Sure.
Okay, thank you.
I have a question.
So, like, the case underscore, double colon, et cetera, the first underscore, how does it know to take the first element and not, like, the first half of the list or something?
Oh, because it's this double colon.
so the only way you can have
a double colon like you couldn't have
in lists
you can't have like
this
oops
I'm going to use x
instead of the underscore
this
with a double colon
and then anything means that this is a single element.
Okay, thank you.
Yeah, you have to look at, I would look at,
if you were to go to list, the implementation of list in Scala,
which you can probably look up online somewhere,
or if you have an IDE set up, you can click into it,
you would look for the unapplied method on this,
and you would see the cases that it looks like.
But this syntax means that this is a single element.
You could do xs three colons.
I don't know if you can see that,
that I just wrote on the board,
it's maybe a little small,
but three colons, ys,
this would actually match a list followed by another list.
Actually, it would be, yeah, a list depended to another list.
I don't actually know if that would work
because how would it know what to assign to XS and what to assign to YS right?
So that may not work but it's because this double colon has a single
element on the left. It's a good question. Okay so we did it empty so let's do head.
What's the return type on head?
It.
Why?
the first one so this is the first one the first element is okay so here we're
going to do excess match okay what do we want
Okay, and I heard you say check if it's empty.
I don't.
Let's hold that thought for a second.
You're not wrong.
Well, let's start with what you said.
So we're going to do, I don't know how it is on the slide because I don't remember.
Let's try it.
So we have x, so here we're going to do underscores because we don't care what the tail is.
We only care about this, so we're going to return that.
And now you said something about checking if I'm emptying.
So that to me sounds like that case where I have a nil.
What do I do?
Say again?
Return nil, I guess.
Return nil.
Would that work?
Would that compile?
No.
Why not?
Nil is not an int.
It's not an int.
It's a list of ints, or in this case, it's a list of ints.
It could be a list of ints.
In this case, we're dealing with ints.
So what do we think about our Java life?
What do we do with Java?
Return null.
So we hate that in Scotland.
We don't return null.
I have my skin crawl.
So we also hate exceptions.
But for this class, the answer for right now is exceptions.
We'll get to another way to do it later in the course.
There's something called an option.
So we would throw.
This is arguably better than returning null.
I don't even know if you can return null for an int in Scala.
I don't use null very much, right?
Null is evil.
So we'll just do no such exception.
You don't actually have to put the parentheses if there's no parameters.
Yeah, man.
Would it be better to do in Scala anyway, better to do that or before the match statement
have a require that requires the list not be empty?
Which one is better performance-wise?
I don't think it's going to matter.
performance-wise. If you do a require it's going to do an extra check. I mean the cost of that is
so minimal it doesn't matter. It's going to check and see if it's empty. The other thing you'll run
into probably is the compiler. I don't think the compiler will complain. You run the risk of
getting if you if you don't actually have the case nil here. I can't remember like if it only throws
an error when you actually pass it something that doesn't match. But you want to, normally
in our Scala, when we compose these case statements, we want these match statements. They're not
statements, they're expressions, sorry. These match expressions. We want to cover all possible
cases in the set of cases. And that doesn't mean that you have to enumerate them all,
you can get away with this because you can throw away. You can also bind that to like
y, y, s. You could bind it to x, which would overwrite, like it wouldn't overwrite, it
would create a new line. I can't remember actually, I would probably would change that
to y, y, s or something if I wanted to do that. But that would bind to, y, s would just
be bound to either nil or some other list, some other non-nil list. Okay, let's see what
we got here. Okay, so it did on the slide it was the only thing different is that
it did the 0 case first and it probably doesn't do that. Okay, so that's... in this
case they used y as well. All right. And then let's look at tail... whoops! They don't want the answer yet.
So tail...
Oh, well.
Well not.
The rename is tail.
And then, what is the return type on tail?
List event.
So this time it's a list event and not an int.
Does everybody understand why?
because the tail is some other list that is after the head tail.
Okay. I have to remember to write the equal sign.
If you don't put the equal sign,
In old Scala, you would have to, in Scala 2,
you would have to, you always would have to have a brace for
compound expression in here, and the default was to make the return type unit, which is
that we want to void. But generally we would type in colon unit equals because it's clearer.
All right, so in this case we have to change this. So what do we want to do here?
And a score and three columns.
I'm going to use ys here.
Ys, okay.
What did you say?
So I thought maybe we can have a three colon.
Three colons?
Yeah.
Oh no, we don't want that.
That's, three colons are generally, if you're using it as not in a match statement, if
you're appending a list.
Yeah, no, we want to decompose.
So we're decomposing the list.
We have some head element, which we don't care about, and some tail, which could be
no, it could be another list.
So, we would return ys here.
And then if we got nil, I guess we would still row.
So I erase that for no reason, no such element exception.
So here, in again, has the nil first.
So many of these list operations are built in.
So I wrote them this way with the list as the parameter,
but the actual list type has a head method,
and a tail method, and it is empty method.
And the only difference is that instead of the parameter here,
it actually looks at the data that the list is holding on to.
Okay, so here's our summary.
Pattern matching is used to decompose lists,
tuples, and objects into their components.
Pattern matching branches and lines variables.
Every one of these case args, arrow, sometimes it's called fat arrow too.
it's like equal arrow but it's arrow body is a function.
And the first matching function in the list of cases is the one that gets evaluated.
So it checks to see if it matches, if it doesn't match,
then it moves on to the next one and checks the next one, and
it keeps going until it finds the first one that matches.
So you might have multiple ones that match, but it's only the first one that matters.
Another thing you can do with pattern matching, which we don't really do here.
If I have, if I want, it's hard to, let me see if I can come up with,
yeah, let's, later on in the course, we're gonna talk about
what in Java we know as generics.
So I'm gonna put x there.
And I'm gonna have access as a list of X.
You know what?
Let's just A because we have too many Xs going here.
We'll just call it A.
So this is A.
So I've parameterized A, and I'm gonna return.
In this case, I'm not gonna call it tail.
I'm just going to say print tail.
And here, I'm going to return unit,
which is the equivalent of our void.
I'm going to do something sort of contrived.
So what I'll do is xs match.
and this is what I want to show you, case ys.
So what I did here was I used a type annotation on this variable I'm binding to.
This is a single colon.
What I'm saying is, okay, if I have a list of ints,
so this is a list of A.
If I have, this A can be anything.
You're used to that with Java
where you have, like, generics and stuff.
But now we're saying, well, all right,
if I got a list of ints here,
then I'm going to, like, print.
And maybe I've got some more, some different cases.
So instead of print, I'll just print.
That's what happens when I do this on the fly.
Print list or print.
So, maybe I'll say print line got ints.
say YS.MakesString, I'm going to pass it comma.
What this will do is create the string dot ints and then have this is the interpolation
because I have the S here.
This is going to then call this function internally and it's going to build this string internally
You can splice it in here, and that'll be what it prints,
but the thing I'm trying to point out is matching.
On this, you can do that by using a typing.
I could also say case YS, this string,
and then do something else.
You would have to have case underscore,
if you have a list of .
So you need to include that so that if you had a list of,
it's a bad idea, duck, maybe we have ducks later on in the course,
I have classes that are ducks.
If you have a list of ducks, then this would match and
maybe you would print out like did not get .
This is very contract,
The whole point of this was to just show you this syntax here, which you can do.
I find that comes up sometimes in my work.
All right, we're at a nice, natural stopping point for our break.
Let's come back at 7.35.
See you in a little bit.
Oh, if you're on the call and you came in late, just let me
know so I can help everybody.
But if you came in late, let me know so I can do it.
Professor, I don't doubt.
OK, hang on a second.
So pattern matchup doesn't follow a specific set of all as in let's say, let's
take the isFD function for example.
So if case underscore comes first instead of case null.
Yeah.
What happens if these is FD is FF.
Oh, we just under for those.
Yeah.
If you do the underscore first, it will match anything in return false.
So the order does matter.
I don't remember how I did it on the board.
I think I did it.
No.
Did I do nil after?
On the board I remember.
For which one?
We did this one on the board.
We did nil first.
You did nil first.
Yeah, I did do nil first.
I didn't think about it.
Because later on, I did it the other way.
But yeah, if you did this so, the order matters, right?
So if it would match, nil would match this.
But because we've avoided nil matching that by putting nil first.
So it does that in order.
So the order of the case statements, the case expressions matter.
We're gonna go do something like that.
We'll try it.
I have been doing good, but it's pretty good.
I don't know.
I love these...
Let's check the video.
aí
Thank you.
Yes.
I'm going to get to the next video.
Here is the top.
I can't believe that I've been using this one.
The
Oh
we will see how it works
This is a complete version of the product.
you
Thank you.
We are going to use a little bit of food.
We are going to be able to eat this.
We will be able to eat it.
We will be able to eat this.
I don't know.
I'm going to get to it.
I'm not saying that.
...
Thank you.
I'm going to get some of the other half.
my
Let's go.
Thank you.
so
I love you.
Again, I will go ahead and spend time on the other side.
I will tell you how much it is.
And now I'm going to show you how to draw a line in the background.
Alright, I'll pick it up.
So our next topic is Scala classes, so we're used to Java and some of you may have worked
C++ which are languages so we'll look at how classes work in Scala.
All right.
So, we're dealing with object-oriented programming.
We're dealing with complex data.
We are encapsulating data with functionality.
So we're going to talk about classes and objects in Scala and what they are.
We're going to use class parameters to initialize, query, and modify object values.
And we'll use Scala objects to implement singletons.
We'll also talk about methods.
So this is basically taking what you know about OO stuff, like from your Java life,
and figuring out how that works in Scala.
So we can define a class.
So in this case we have a class C. That's how you do it, that's the syntax.
So this particular class has one constructor with parameters F1, F2, and F3.
To instantiate it we would do this, we would call new C.
The instance of C is allocated on the heap, so this is what we're used to in Java, right?
We call new, we get something on the heap.
When Scala runs, it runs on the JPM.
So it's the same underlying virtual machine, essentially.
After the colon here, you would usually indent,
and there would be stuff here, methods would be defined.
But actually, anything that's in here that is not a method
is essentially going to be the body of the constructor.
So the constructor is unified.
In Java you have to write a separate constructor if you want it.
It's implemented sort of like the same-ish syntax as a method but
it's a little bit different because it doesn't have a return type.
Usually it's like public and then the name of the class and
then any of the parameters it can pass to the constructor.
And then you would have implementation where you would actually have places
where you would be setting class variables or anything like that.
Well, in Scala, anything, anytime you see expressions here that are not function,
I'm sorry, method declarations, that's just the body of the constructor executed.
So just like in Java, when we do this kind of thing, we have,
you can think of this as, here's our object allocated on the heap.
This is a C.
It has F1, F2, and F3.
And these are ints.
And the values are going to be, in this case here, we have 2, 3, and 5.
So F1's going to get 2.
F2's going to get 3.
And F3's going to get 5.
This is curious here.
There's an F1, which has no qualifier in front of it.
Here we have an F2, which has val and F3, which has var.
So that just tells us some things about whether the fields are publicly visible or
not.
So the F1 would not be publicly visible.
The F2 will be.
The F3 will also be.
You don't say public.
it's just because it's val or var,
you would have to say private var,
I think if you wanted it to be variable,
mutable, and private,
I don't remember because it's
not often something I would do.
So you have this and then this is
a capital C because that's the type.
Now out here in my calling code,
I have a variable C of type C,
capital C, and it's referring to this thing.
So this is very similar to what we have in Java.
So we say c is a reference to some instance.
Okay, so class parameters simultaneously declare
constructors and accessor methods.
That's what I was trying to say before without those words.
So components of the class body are public by default.
So if I have this def double
this is going to be a public method called double.
This is going to double the implementation is taking the value of x
Double it, wrapping some value, some integer value.
So X is private and immutable.
The constructor is automatically going to be public,
you could actually declare it private, I do that sometimes.
But in this class, it's not necessary.
And then double is going to be public.
If I were to express that code in Java,
that's what it would look like.
So, you're all familiar with Java so this is a C1 you declare a class.
It has some private final int x.
It has a constructor that takes an x and this is the body of the constructor.
Notice inside the body of the constructor in Java,
I have to actually do this thing where I actually take the parameter that I'm past
and then save it off in my instance variable.
And I have my public int double method, which will return x plus x.
So that's the Java translation for a Java translation.
So immutable class parameters can be initialized but not modified.
So here x is public and immutable, and I can never change x because it's a bell.
It gets to be public because you sent val.
If you think about it, since it's immutable,
do we actually care if it's visible outside?
Maybe, maybe not.
But it's not as dangerous as having a public instance
variable in Java, because your calling code
could actually change the value of that if it's public.
And in Scala, this is public.
But because it's val, it's immutable and can't be changed.
so it's less than a three.
So if I want to express this C2 thing in Java,
I'm going to get that.
So similarly, I have my x.
It's private here.
Personally, I might have implemented this with public
as long as this is final because based
on what I just said, if it's final, nobody can change it.
So you might want to expose it, you might not.
Depends.
But if you're going to do that and you
want to access the value of x. If you're going to make it private then you have to
call a public method which will return the value and then you have your double
like before.
So mutable class parameters can be changed even after initialization. So if
if I have this class C3, I have this mutable, var x.
X is public and mutable, as I just said.
And that's what it looks like expressed in Java.
But I can, in Java, we typically write a setter.
So in our setter, we would have this dot x equals x.
I wouldn't have, like in Scala, I don't have to implement my getter and
my setter, because if I have var and val,
I can do this kind of thing.
Usually, we don't make bars like our classes.
So in Scala, would you type like C3 dot set x?
No.
Oh, no, OK.
So in this example here, I was hoping that I don't remember
that, yeah, it doesn't have it.
So if I had like val c equals mu c3, and I pass 42.
Oh, I don't need .
I've been writing Rust at work all day.
If I have that, I can now say c dot x equals c dot x plus 1.
I can do that outside of C, because it's var and it's public.
So you don't have to, as your question was, do I have to type set x, no.
In fact it wouldn't work.
Matt.
So the C being about, is that more pertaining to that you can't point C at a different instance of C3?
Yeah, I can't update C. So I can't update what C refers to actually using this picture.
this is in this case, we have a C3, right?
These, these are different now, right?
So here we just have x.
And if I do that statement there, I'm sorry, that expression there,
C dot x equals C dot x plus one, this would actually update to 43.
If I declared C over here as a val,
I can't change what C refers to.
If I declared it as a var, instead I'm
going to make this D because I want a different name.
Now I can say D equals new C3 100.
I can change what D points to because it's a bar.
So this little qualifier here applies
to the thing it's referring to.
So class body.
So the class body is going to contain field declarations,
val or var.
So these actually execute as part of the constructor
when the constructor, when you say new class, like new C,
it will actually go through and take these parameters
and do these evaluations and set these valves and bars,
and it just executes that once.
It will print here, so it'll execute this print line.
You hit this def, it's actually just defining the method,
so that's not gonna execute, because it's,
this doesn't mean defer, it means defined,
but it's deferring, there isn't gonna actually
be an execution of M until you call M somehow.
But I cannot reassign to F1, F2, or F4,
because F1 is not declared to be variable.
F2 is a VAL, and F4 is also a VAL.
is also a vowel but F5 and F3 are bars so you can change the data there.
I think also this NC is optional and this NM, it does make it easier to read but you
don't necessarily have to type that.
So a val field, val x equals 1, we say that this is strict, we're going to talk later
on about strictness and non-strictness, we'll get there, but this is strict, it's initialized
once.
So what this really means is that this expression of the rate of the equal sign, whatever it
is, is evaluated once.
In this case, it's really simple, it's just a number, it's 1, so that's evaluated to
1.
And it's stored in x, so x is going to refer to that 1, and it will never execute that
So if this were some complex expression over here,
it would do it once because it's valid.
So def is gonna be, in this case it's a non-parameterized method.
So that means there's no parameters that we're passing to this method y.
But def is definitely defining a method y.
And there's no parameters.
But it's going to evaluate this thing to the right of the equal sign every single time.
That you call .
So if this were some complex expression,
it would re-execute that code every single time.
In this case, it's a two, it re-executes that.
But that's just going to evaluate to two.
So it's not going to do much.
And then this lazy vowel.
So lazy vowel.
This is a memoized def.
So this will defer the initialization of Z.
So Z will not have any definition until later.
So if I have an instance of C, and I call Z, or I try to access Z,
it will execute that once and memoize or save it in Z,
the value that you evaluate as X plus Y to will be saved in Z,
And then it will never execute that again, it's only executed once.
So this is useful sometimes.
So expressed in Java.
I would have to do, I've got my final int x equals 1 so
that's equivalent to that val x equals 1.
I would have my public int y, so here's my method y, that returns to,
and every single time it's going to execute this code,
this is how you would understand this code if you look at it in Java.
And then I would have, this is like this, how you would do this lazy thing.
This is a little bit weird to me.
So you would have declared this storage for
an integer called z and you would set it equal to null.
And then when z gets called, this code will check for null.
And if it's null, it will say x plus y.
That's the same as what we have over there.
And then it will take the result and store it in our z here.
It will actually box it up into a capital I integer, right?
This is the reference type integer.
And then it will return this.
Then it will unbox it for the return.
So it's a little bit subtle what's going on there.
But you've hopefully seen some stuff like this in Java.
But if z happens to not be null,
like there was some value stored there,
then it would skip over this whole thing
and just return whatever was there before.
So that's what that lazy vowel means.
This kind of shows you in Java
in a language you already know, hopefully well.
This is why Scala, like this is why I can switch back
and forth between Java and Scala,
because I read that and I think that because I was a Java person for a long time.
But I don't think like in terms of the syntax, I think in terms of like what it means in the memory of the computer,
in the memory of the virtual machine.
So then we have these things called objects.
So an object is going to declare a single instance, which is accessible through the object name.
So this is I don't know if you've ever seen in like software engineering,
There's like a single team design pattern.
This is a gang of four design pattern
that has been defined by the software engineering
community.
It's basically what it means is you
have a single instance of something.
So you get language support, so built into the language.
You don't have to do all this gobbledygook
like you have to do in Java to make it work.
You just declare an object.
So when I have an object, I can say C.count directly.
I don't actually say new on this object C.
I just access the fields of C or the methods of C.
So here, what I'm doing is, when the class loads,
it actually will set count equal to zero.
This is like in the class loader like in Java.
And then in my code, I can say, oh, I'm
going to update C dot count, this var.
It's var, so I can update it.
And I'm going to update it to C dot count plus one.
So in Java you would do this, you can do this.
So I said gobbledygook, the usual pattern in software engineering is you would have
a constructor that would be private.
And you would have a static get method that would check to see if the instance was null.
And then if it is null it would instantiate and then return the thing that you instantiate
it otherwise it would be like that example from before where it would be that lazy val.
thing that's completely separate.
But in Java, the equivalent of this.
So this is implemented the same way.
When I compile this to bytecode here,
this main method in my object C, it's implemented the same way
as Java would have static.
Just like in Java, you would when
you run this particular program, it'll
execute this main program.
I could in Scala also run C, and that would be the main program.
So, method main must be declared in an object.
Like I said, these are instantiated.
These objects are instantiated once and the program starts up, so at class load time.
So in Java, we have static versus non-static.
So static components belong to a class.
And when I say that, I mean the definition of a class.
All other components belong to an instance of a class.
In Java, we have this distinction between class methods and
instance methods, right?
Or class fields and instance fields.
So if they're class fields, they're static.
Class methods are static.
Instance fields are not.
Instance methods are not.
So here's, in Java I have this, I have class C.
I have a static and a static, right?
So I have a static int f2 and a static method m2 that returns an int,
takes an instance of some other C.
If I wanna implement this in Scala,
I use something called a companion object.
So I'm gonna see what that looks like.
The companion object is gonna replace the static things.
All the data and methods belong to objects,
companion is related to other instances. So this is what it looks like. So typically in Scala,
we define our class. And instead of putting any of our static stuff like right in the class,
like we did in Java, we define an object with the same name. So that makes it a companion. Usually
we put it in the same file, and we put it underneath the definition of a class. And so
this is a companion object. And this contains all the things that are analogous to the static
methods and fields over here that's how we do it okay so if we wanted to
implement a matrix in Scala here's a way we can do it
So I'm going to use IntelliJ.
So here's my class matrix.
What I've gotten here, so in this initial code, I don't have, I don't have any parameters
or anything, so you can just leave off the colon, right.
The way we're going to implement this is by having an array.
An array and array.
So we're going to define our class.
And we're going to start by having a contract.
So when we, I'm just going to do this kind of as an example.
So when we construct our matrix, we're
going to require that the data is not equal to null, right?
Because we don't want the data that we're holding on to
to be null, and we're going to say data.nonempty.
So just like in Java, I haven't completed this expression
yet, but just like in Java, if we check this not null,
how we can call methods on it.
If we had not checked for null, and we got a null,
we would throw a null pointer exception, just like in Java.
So this will short-circuit.
So if this is not null, sorry.
If it is null, it won't continue executing the rest of it.
If it is not null, then it will check.
So that's not null is true.
So it's now going to check the next argument to the boolean
And then, we're going to do this data.forAll.
I'll explain this in a second.
And I need a comma over here.
Otherwise, it won't.
That's a different part.
It's a different.
Oh.
Sorry.
I need an and.
So what I'm saying here is, I'm gonna take my data array, and I'm gonna go through each
element, so that's what that for all is.
And when you do a for all, each of the expressions, so you're gonna evaluate this expression for
each element.
And when you say for all, you're saying they all have to be true.
If any one of them is not true, then that will return false.
Okay, so data for all, so what we're saying here is, each array,
inside that outer wrapped array has to have the same length right if they don't
have the same length then you don't really have a matrix right and then what
we do here is we write all rows must have the same number of columns. Now this
is going to go off to the end here and I'm going to like
hit new line and just kind of move over here.
So actually, usually the way you do this,
my team is very pedantic, right?
So they want me to do that.
They want me to put each parameter on its own line
when it gets to be too long.
So that is a totally valid thing to do.
So what are we doing is we're calling this require thing.
So I think Matt, you mentioned require earlier,
or we actually saw it too.
Not to single you out, I just remember you saying it.
But if we look at required, this is included in scala in the pre-def.
That's what, see, it comes up as pre-def.
What does required do?
Well, required is going to take a Boolean expression and
it's going to say if the requirement evaluates to false or evaluated to false,
it's gonna throw in a legal argument exception and
it's gonna construct the message like this.
This syntax is a little funny.
We get to that later in the course.
actually doesn't evaluate this expression, it's called a thunk, a little preview, doesn't
evaluate this expression until it needs it. We'll get to that when we talked about, when
we talk about non-strippness. But, that's what required us, so we'll throw an exception
if we don't meet the condition that's past here, the precondition. Alright. So that's
That's the beginning of our matrix.
Now we're going to say rows is going to be data.length, and calls is going to be data.0.length.
Now IntelliJ likes to highlight this stuff as red because I didn't actually put the type
annotation so this is what I was talking about earlier.
is why I use IntelliJ, because I can do that.
And it will just add it for me.
It's just super nice.
You need the Scala plugin, by the way, to use IntelliJ.
I don't put a lot of directions on how to do that.
You can figure it out if you want, or you can use vscode,
or you can use whatever you want.
I have a suspicion that I will eventually
start using vscode, because I'm going
to be using it for Rust later, when
I start to do actual production work.
So now we're going to define a method that
adds two matrices together.
So in Scala we can do this by, our operators can be
methods, method names.
So let's say I'm going to take, so that my method name is other,
I'm sorry, my method name is plus and I'm
going to take a parameter other.
It's going to take another matrix.
And it's going to return a matrix.
So this is going to return another matrix.
We need that equals sign there.
So, when we return the result,
we're going to need a new matrix, right?
So we'll start by saying valResult equals array
dot valDimension,
and we'll use int passing rows and columns.
problems. So that's going to construct a new array and it's going to give me this little
red squiggle until I return something, a proper thing. Sometimes when I'm doing this, it gets
annoying, so I put that in there and that three question marks actually will throw a
not implemented error. That's what that is in case you wondered. It's in the
predefined as well. Okay so then what I'm going to do is I'm gonna go through the
four.
Now here, this is different than what we talked about earlier.
I'm actually having only one 4 expression.
We'll put ij is this dot theta ij plus other dot theta ij.
going to add my for again that's optional you don't have to write that. And then down
here I'm going to instead of the three question marks I'm going to return new matrix passing
result, and my paper doesn't even have it on there.
The last expression is what we return.
So we're constructing a new matrix and passing this in a row.
All right. So, we will also implement toString, and this is a little bit of a preview.
So, because in Scala, every instance of a class, or every class definition, this actually extends from any ref.
And because any ref is equivalent to java.lang.object,
we can define a toString, which comes from Java,
and we can say that we're overriding it
because it comes from object.
But any ref is how we refer to that .
So I will do something slightly different here.
We will talk about this, I believe, next week.
data.map, we're going to take each row,
and we're going to do row.mixString.
This is similar to what we saw in homework.
So this business here is, I'm gonna take data, and for each row I'm gonna call makeString.
What that will do is it will take each element and separate by spaces.
And then that will result in an array of strings.
And then I'm gonna call makeString with that array of strings and
I'm gonna add the new line there.
So that's a way that we can define class.
So we can instantiate, so
instead of my hello world here,
I'm gonna put an actual implementation.
So we can say l m equals new matrix array.
Array 1, 2, 3.
Array 1, 5, 6.
So now I can do things like m.data 0, 0, 0, equals 10.
So I can update one of the cells by doing that.
So let's run this and see.
Actually, let's actually, to make sure that we know what we have, let's put a print line
there before we change it.
And then I'll do a print line with nothing so that we just get a new line to separate
it and run this and see if it runs.
All right, so our output, our initial,
you can ignore all this crap.
There's something in Java that doesn't allow
things that Scala is doing.
You can ignore this crap up here.
I tried to turn it off but I can't.
It's like a lot of time and I have to put it.
So anyway, we started with a matrix that looks like that.
One, two, three.
And then we have four, five, six.
Notice that in our matrix, we're using,
calling toString on these arrays.
So in Scala we actually have something more interesting
than the Java2String, which I think just gives you
like an address of some hexadecimal string.
That's kind of nice.
And then I updated it to have 10 here,
so we printed that out.
So using this mutable array though,
can actually break things.
So if we wanted to say, we could do something like this.
Whoops.
Say m.data0 equals array 10, and then printlnm.
Now we're not going to, we're going to break the class invariant, the invariant, right?
So I should probably throw in another print line.
Yeah.
Just right there.
Throw that in.
This will break our matrix because now we broke it, right?
So this is the bad thing about exposing things like arrays or mutable data in your class definition.
So we won't actually fix it, but the way you fix it is you have to make the data private to inside the class,
and then you have to have methods that are checking to see what you're doing to make sure you're not breaking anything.
So you wouldn't want to expose the underlying array outside the address.
This is the same kind of thing you have to deal with in Java as well.
But this is just kind of an example of how you would create these things.
I have another example that I won't do.
We'll talk later tonight about algebraic data types.
So I have an example for that.
But I don't know if I'll get to that, so I might have to do it later next week.
All right.
All right, so that was just a little example of matrix class.
For some reason, I have to slow down,
my computer slow down.
Here we go, so summary.
So class parameters and
factory methods replace constructors.
And there's built in support for
the singleton designed by using statics,
underlying statics for these companion objects.
So classes have class C with F is an int.
This is private and immutable.
Val is going to be public and immutable, and
Var is going to be public and immutable.
So that's what you see here.
With objects, this replaces static from Java.
So object O has an N is going to be 10.
And I can get my own N and get a copy of it by accessing it.
I can't change it, cuz it's valid.
If it were var, I could change it.
Companion objects.
So I have a class x, and then an object with the same name, also x.
And I can have methods,
these are equivalent to statics in Java, the ones that are on object.
So they can have access to private elements of their companion.
it compiles them to static, the equivalent of static methods.
Like what you would write Java, it would compile to a certain kind of bytecode.
Scala would compile to that same bytecode.
Yeah.
If you have objects within classes underneath that are different.
That would just be the regular object, not the whole opinion.
When you say an object within classes.
You're saying an object within classes, what do you?
I was just thinking of like the homework,
because I think they had the game of life object and then
like the different classes.
I'm not sure exactly what you're talking about,
so maybe talk to me after class.
Because there's probably something specific that when I see it,
I'll be able to explain it.
Okay.
So that is classes in Scala.
And now we will talk about algebraic data types.
Okay, so how do we deal with complex data in functional programs?
So we haven't really done a lot of functional programming yet.
We're going to start getting into that next.
Your homework this week is functional programming.
So we're going to identify sums and products in algebraic types.
We're going to use the Scala Enum classes to express algebraic data types.
So these are called, these algebraic data types are called sum types, because they're
actually sums of products, so what does that mean?
Product types are going to combine multiple data elements into one unit.
So tuples and classes are product types.
And the way to think about this is like you have a tuple,
a 3-tuple like this.
With this kind of, if you think about it,
your product is going to be, you can
have all the possible integers in this location here.
You can have all the possible strings,
and there's an infinite number of strings,
and you can have all the possible lists of three
elements of inths, right?
So that's why it's called a product,
Because you're basically, you have some number of elements here.
Some unknown infinite number of elements here and
some infinite number of elements here.
And you multiply that together and you get a product.
Think about it kind of conceptually.
Some types are actually going to distinguish between multiple alternatives.
So earlier tonight, we saw this type character.
They had a list of int or list of something.
I think it was int or list of int.
That's a union type, so that just means that the type is expressed as saying it's
either an int, in this case, it's either an int or it's a string.
This is actually, when we do this type of thing, class A and
then class B extends A and class C extends A, this is actually a discriminated union.
What that means is that instances of B and instances of C are also As, and you know that
it's B, or you know that it's C at runtime.
So you can click this link, it'll take you to Wikipedia, and we'll talk about algebraic
data types in programming languages.
I think it will refer to, yes, it will say, especially in computer programming, but especially
in functional programming and type theory.
So product types are named for the Cartesian products of sets.
That's why I said this before.
So if you have all the elements of X, Y times, or Cartesian product, Y,
so you have your Xs are from X and your Ys are from Y, and
you have all the possible values of X that could be X and
all the possible values of Y that could be Y.
So we can define that with a case class definition for a product of int and string.
So I can do that like that.
And that gives me the pairs, right?
You could also use the tuple.
We can construct new instances.
So new is not necessary with case classes.
It's just a scholar family.
You can extract elements with pattern matching.
So if I have a reference C to this case class,
I can say match.
If I'm matching on case C, and I'm binding the elements to A and B.
So the x gets bound to A and the y gets bound to B.
And here I'm just returning the first element.
The X is returned because A got bound to whatever X had.
So Scala case classes.
So the compiler, when you write case class,
the compiler does a bunch of things for you.
So you get class parameters.
They're going to be visible and immutable.
So they're going to be automatically vowels,
even though on the other slide deck I had,
like it wasn't a case class.
And if you didn't say that it was a val, it wasn't a val.
In case classes, they're automatically going to be vales.
So if I do val c, type c, and then I call, well,
this is actually ultimately going
to call a method called apply, which the compiler generates
for you.
You can look that up in your textbook,
which will then take the two parameters
and then pass it into the constructor.
I don't know both of their constructor.
So here, I'm going to take the first element and bind it to A.
And then I'm going to try to assign to X,
but that won't work because I can't reassign to a VAL.
The compiler will complain.
You get a sensible two-string implementation.
I would argue with that in business
when I work with case classes in my Scala code at work.
The two-string implementation can be useless
because there are so many fields, and many
of them are the same types, I'm usually
modeling transactions at your bank.
So there are lots of fields.
There's balances.
There's amounts of transaction.
There's running balances.
There's some other balance.
I don't know.
There's all this crap.
When you print all this out and there's
20-something fields, it's not very useful.
So we actually usually write something else to tell me
what the fields are so that when I'm looking at it printed out
in a log or something, I can make sense of it.
So it's sensible for small classes, I guess.
But I disagree with that.
You're gonna get the companion object
with the apply method, which is gonna be used
to construct instances.
And notice, this is, so you're gonna automatically get,
the compiler will generate a companion object,
and it will create an apply method,
which will invoke the constructor.
I said that a minute ago, but you're gonna get that for free.
You're gonna get pattern matching support.
So I mentioned this earlier, unapply method.
These are called extractors in your Scala textbook.
You're also going to get hash code.
I don't think it's on the slide, but it's really useful
because we went through that whole exercise in data
structures one, where if you took data structures one with me,
I taught you how to write a good hash code,
and there was an exam question on it.
I don't have to do it anymore, because in Scala,
I write case classes, and I usually get a hash code for free,
and it's a good implementation of a hash code.
Good meaning that when I use it in a Hash Map
or in some kind of data structure,
it's going like a, yeah, Hash Map,
like a separate chaining Hash Map,
it will have the,
Hash code will have reduced,
minimize the number of collisions which is key.
Okay, so that was product types.
Some types.
So these are named for sums or union of sets.
So if we have this here, we have X union Y,
I have what this means is I have Z such that
Z is an element of X or Z is an element of Y.
We actually have this when we do sum types in Scala.
We have a co-product or a disjoint union of sets.
So this is slightly different, it's just different notation so don't freak out.
But this just means that, I guess you can write it this way with the circle and the plus or
you can write it this way with the union and the plus.
What this is saying is I have x such that x is an element of x.
Union with y such that y is an element of y.
But notice this 0 and 1.
0 and 1 are always going to be constant.
So when I have an element of x, I'm actually thinking of it with this label
0 when I have an element of Y I'm thinking of it with this label 1 and
that just tells me where it came from it tells me that it came from x or it came
from y so that's called the discriminated union I believe because it
discriminates between which one it tells you which one it came from so elements
are tagged to indicate their source of the class of the element so before we
had that example of class a and the class b extends a and class c extends a
when we know at run time which one it is so this expresses this idea of a sum type.
So. This joint union, so if we want to express this with a Scala enumeration, in this case
we only have two colors in our DePaul world. Luckily my undergrad is also blue and white.
So in this enumeration of colors we only have blue or white.
I also can have a disjoint union of a value and an operator.
So if I have an expression in some language, I could have a number or I could have a plus.
And if I have a plus, I have some expression on the left, and then I have a plus sign usually,
like this is how we think of it, and then some expression on the right.
So the definitions can be recursive.
So here they're recursive because I have an expression,
one of the possibilities is a plus, and
that plus would be composed of two sub-expressions, if you will.
So they're recursive.
So, in other words, this L can be a number or given the definition here,
a number or a plus.
And the same with R.
So if I wanna create instances,
I can say valv equals color dot blue.
If I want to create instances of expressions, I can do this, I can call.
So when I declare an enum I get the things I get with a case class also show up.
So I get the ability to call the apply method,
which is what you see here without the word new.
So it's creating a new number with its x is going to have the value 3.
Here we have a plus, which is going to take that 3 and put it in the left expression.
And a number 5, which is going to put it in the right expression.
So that's an example of how we can do that.
All right, so the functional calculator,
I'm not going to do it because we're running short on time.
But I'll post it to the Discord.
And actually, I'll post it.
I think I'm going to have to modify the course site
to add the code snippets.
I took it out before because I wasn't using it,
but I'm going to add it back.
I don't always use the code snippets,
but this time around I'm trying to.
It was in time.
Okay, so here's a disjoint union, scala enum,
and using pattern matching, which we covered earlier,
to decompose.
So if I get some expression, I'm going to match.
If I get a number, so I'm evaluating the expression.
If I get a number with some x value, I'm just gonna return that x and
remember this is gonna be an int because it was defined that way.
So number as an int.
Otherwise I'm gonna take plus L and R and I'm gonna call eval recursively.
I'm gonna pass L, the left expression, so
it will recursively do this whole thing.
And then I'm gonna come back and then do it again for
expression and evaluate that and then do this addition operation and then the
results will be returned. So in both cases we're gonna end up with an int
because eval returns an int. By the way, with recursion in Scala, you have to
include the return type. So normally if you're not doing recursion, you can get
away without the return type. But if you're doing recursion the compiler needs a little help.
So if I want to create an instance and pass it to eval.
So here what I've done is I've said I'm going to have this expression.
And that expression is I have a times.
And inside, I have on the left side, a plus.
And the right side, I have a number 2.
And that's my times expression.
And then inside the plus, I have a three and a five.
A number three and a number five.
So the way we would think about this is we would add 3 plus 5 and then that would be 8.
And then we would multiply 8 times 2 and get 16.
So if we called eval on this expression v, so v is the variable, is the val that we're creating.
So we're just referring to this whole thing and we're passing it into eval.
And so it's going to do all this chugging and come up with answer 16.
So if we looked at a linked list, what are the states that we have in a linked list?
We talked about this earlier.
So what case classes and case objects?
So we're going to do this as my list.
So, in my list, we have an empty and a con cell at least one element.
So this is not the list that you get in Scala, this is our own version that we're creating.
We're going to define it as an enumeration.
In fact, in the Scala book that has functional programming patterns, and this is one of the
exercises that have you define your own list.
They have you define, later on, we'll talk about options.
They'll have you define your own option.
Like this this doesn't give you the nice double colons that we're used to, but
this kind of gives you a way to think about it.
You either have an empty list or a cons.
This is equivalent to our nil in Scala and
this is equivalent to whatever they call it.
Like the non nil, the con cell, I think they call it con.
Notice the head is an int.
In this case, this my list is a list of ints.
There's no type grammar.
And a tail is just another list.
So very similar conceptually to what we've been doing.
This case classes and case objects is a little bit weird.
Before Scala 3, we didn't have enumeration.
So we would have a, what we would do
is define a sealed trait.
The key word sealed in Scala means that any subclasses
have to be defined in the same file.
Otherwise the compiler will complain if you try to define a subtype of trait.
The trait is like an interface.
So if you say SEALD trait and you try to implement that interface, that trait, somewhere else
in another file, compiler will complain.
The reason for that is if you because we have pattern matching in Scala, the compiler needs
to know all the possible things that implement that trait.
So that's why we would use SEALD.
When you use enumeration, you don't need SEALD because it's automatic.
It's gotta be defined right there under the enumeration.
So this business over here about case classes and objects,
in the version where we used the sealed trade,
I'll actually do it on the board just to make it clear.
So if I do a sealed trade, this is Scalature.
So if you ever see it, that's what it is.
So sealed.
And then you would have case, object empty.
empty and case class cons and you have head int and tail.
so again I can define this and this is you can actually do this in Scala 3 too it's equivalent
and if you're cross compiling like I do all the time I have to do this because I can't use syntax
that's specific to Scala 3 when I'm cross compiling this is how we did it in iterations before oh I
forgot the close one but the sealed business just tells the compiler okay everything that oh I
I left off extends.
See this is what happens.
I would have caught that when I was testing it would not compile when I was
trying to do something with my list.
And this will be extends.
My list.
So literally when you do this in Scalic 3, you're getting all that.
It's gonna compile to the same time.
So how would I create an empty list?
That's simply you would use empty, so, lxs is empty.
You have to do this import statement because it can't see these things inside.
This corresponds to that previous slide, this empty is the case object,
it's the case class and the reason it's a class is because you have to instantiate
it with, do it instantiate with different values.
So that works that way and then if I want to create an instance of a list,
I would nest the cons and terminate with empty.
So here I have that list one, two, three.
The way to do that is I'm gonna start with empty and
I'm gonna use it to compose a cons with a three.
And then I'm gonna use that thing to compose another cons with a two and
then use all that to compose yet another cons with a one.
This is what I've been talking about with this apply business.
So, here I have a companion object, myList,
and this is what apply looks like.
So in this case I have apply that takes a variable list,
variable length argument list called elements.
These are ints and it's gonna return a myList
and we'll say, well, if my,
I think this will end up being a list or a sequence,
I can't remember what it, internally what it does.
But if this is empty, then I'm gonna return the empty list,
which in my list implementation is empty.
Otherwise, I'm gonna do cons with elems.head and
then I'm gonna recursively call apply with elems.tail.
And this will actually, well, this is an interesting,
there's a different syntax in Scala too.
But this is sort of like taking the tail, and
and it's called a splat operator.
It's like you're taking the list of ints there and
you're expanding it somehow so it can pass as an int star parameter.
Which is the splatted thing.
So, syntax threw me for
a second because I'm used to looking at it in Scala too.
I don't look at it in Scala.
But that's what it's doing.
So it's basically making the tail conform to this parameter type here so
that it can then recursively execute and construct.
So here to create an instance of the list, I no longer have to
do that cons thing, the cons, cons, cons thing I was doing before.
Now I can call my list one, two, three.
So with regular ScholarList, we saw list one, two, three.
That's how that works.
It's the same idea.
It has this apply method.
So that's what's going on.
So our summary, algebraic data types,
that's the sum of products.
So product types will combine multiple data elements.
Tuples and classes are a good way to implement these.
Some types are gonna distinguish between multiple alternatives.
So we can do this with subclasses, class A, class B extends A,
class C extends A, and we can also do this with union types, B or C.
In Scala we have enum and case classes.
So these are the algebraic, this is a way to do algebraic data types.
They're the sum of products.
So these are, and it's actually, notice you have product one, so here's a product,
and then like I said before, anything like this is gonna be a product because
you have all the possible values of i, sorry, all the possible ints,
all the possible strings, and then product two is gonna have all the possible ints,
all the possible ints, all possible ints.
But this is the sum of all these different products,
that's what we're getting at here.
And that gives you algebraic data.
There's another example here, Pinot numbers.
So these are the natural numbers.
So either 0 or some transitive successor of it.
So here's an algebraic data type Pinot natural numbers.
So I have either a 0 or a successor to some other Pinot.
So successor to 0 is 1, successor of successor of 0 is 2,
successor of successor of successor of zero of three and so on.
It just goes on forever.
It's natural.
So if I want to evaluate my p no nat to an int,
I can do it this way.
Here I'm using this,
I'm using this accumulator that I just keep passing down.
So if I get a zero, I just return whatever result.
If I get, oh and this is a default.
So in Scala, we have the ability to do default parameter values.
So if I call this with a q, this will set the result equal to 0,
that's the additive identity, that's why that's there.
So if I get 0, and that's gonna be 0.
And if I get something else, I'll take,
if I have a successor of something, I'll take that something and
pass it in recursively, and then take whatever result I got and add one to it.
so it'll just add one going all the way on down
until it bottoms out.
So if I got a zero,
I will have accumulated the result in here,
and otherwise, if I got a zero and only a zero,
and not like a nested thing,
like, okay, if I said q equals zero instead of all this,
then it would use the default parameter.
If I say q equals successor of successor of successor of zero,
then it will keep adding up from zero all the way down.
And when I hit zero, I'll return themself.
That's just another example.
Here's another example, binary operations tree.
So the data is stored at leaves
and operations are stored at internal nodes.
Internal nodes have left and right subtrees.
So here's a tree of some data type x,
we're gonna abstract out the type.
And then we have leaves, which has a data element.
Or we have a node which has a left tree and a right tree
and then some operation which is expressed
as this function f.
It's gonna take whatever the left evaluates to,
whatever the right evaluates to,
and then combine those two
and produce a new value of type x.
So here's how we would evaluate the tree.
We're gonna call it a fold.
We're going to fold the tree into the result by applying all the intermediate operations.
We do this recursively with pattern matching.
So we get to the leaf, that's just whatever value the leaf holds, the data value.
We bind x to data, and we return that x.
If we have a node with an L and an f is a function or an operation and a right, we're
We're going to recursively call fold on the left,
recursively call fold, as defined here, on the right,
and then apply the operation f,
and whatever the result is of type x, we'll return that.
So this is a recursive expression.
Can you go back one slide?
Yes.
So by case 0 and case suck n, is it evaluating if p is equal to 0 or p is equal to suck n?
Oh yeah, because over here to the right of the equals side, it didn't start a new line like I sometimes do.
This is perfectly valid to start the method definition right here.
So it's evaluating p by saying p match.
OK. You see that?
Yeah.
So it's saying if p is equal to 0, then I'm going to return whatever I got in
this result parameter here. Matt?
So in the enum, here?
Yeah. It's matching based off of the arguments, right?
Could you have a third case with a different name that was also a single parameter of PNOT
or would you have to have a different signature for it to differentiate?
Well you could have other cases, but they would have to be successors.
Yeah, you couldn't have a case, foo, that also takes in Pinot Nat in the enum.
Like it wouldn't be able to differentiate those.
When you say foo, what do you...
Just like up the...
Oh, you mean if there's like a kind of thing here?
Right.
If you were to add another one, would it have to have like a different argument signature?
No, not necessarily.
but you would have to account for that case somehow.
I mean, you've changed the definition of this now.
But if you change the definition,
then you have to account for the case.
But you may not need, I mean, notice that you
have to just evaluate which case it was, right?
So you don't need to change this signature here.
Does that answer your question?
No, I was asking about the signature at the top.
I wasn't really thinking too much about the bottom part.
would just kind of ask about the mechanics of Enum and Scala?
Right. So, I mean, I guess the bottom line is you have to evaluate all the, you have
to, every expression would have to match on one of these cases. So if you added another
case in your definition, you would have to provide that case somehow. But you wouldn't
necessarily change this.
Could you pass in a result to like into PnO2int, like the default is zero?
Yes, that would be totally legal.
You might not want to, or you might want to, maybe you're adding like you,
you have your PnO nat and you're adding it to some other value.
So you would, you could do that.
It's, it would be legal Scala to do that.
Doesn't make much sense, but yeah,
you can do it. Okay, thanks. Did that answer all your questions, Cindy? Because Matt jumped in with
a question, so I want to make sure we got all your questions, too. Oh yeah, it did. Okay, cool.
So then we got through that one. Okay, great. And now for our last topic of the evening,
20 minutes to do 18 slides. Usually I have to multiply by two, that's my standard algorithm,
So we might not get through all this, but we'll see.
So what should be the basic building blocks of computations?
So we're going to identify.
So this is a completely different sort of idea than what we've been talking about so far tonight.
So we're looking at languages, and we're looking at what makes up the language.
So we're going to identify different ways of expressing computations,
And we're gonna identify the difference between statement sequences and compound expression.
So this word sequences and this word expressions are sort of the key ideas here.
I'm sorry, statement, sequence, statement, and expression.
Those words that look similar, I don't know it might, it's been a long time.
So, all right, so Scala.
Here's on the left we have Scala and
we have this expression, this method here.
And then we see that we have, we're setting y equal to,
something, either one or two, depending on the result of this if check, right?
Can I write that same way with somewhat modified syntax in Java or C?
so here I have if x is not equal to 0, 1, else 2, and I'm trying to assign that to y.
So I'm conditionally setting this variable. Is that valid in Java NC?
Somebody says no. You are correct. This is not valid in Java or C.
So that's because in Java and C, if else is a state,
is part of the statement language,
not the expression language.
So and we're going to start differentiating between statements and expressions.
So here is Java and C, this is how we conditionally set a variable.
So here we use this ternary operator, which we're hopefully maybe familiar with.
I don't necessarily cover it much, but in data structures,
But we do have that in Java.
So this just says if x is not equal to 0, then give me 1, otherwise give me 2, and assign
it to y.
So that's perfectly valid.
If I try to write the same kind of thing in Scala, it won't work.
The reason why is because we don't have a ternary operator in the Scala expression language.
Scala doesn't have statements.
Scala has expressions.
That's why you heard me correct myself earlier when I said something about statements.
I got caught at work one day, I was really tired and I was getting ready to come down here to teach.
And I kept saying Scala and I said that statement and I kept correcting myself.
Nobody else on my team does because they don't think about, they're not language geeks like me.
But the if-else is in the Scala expression language.
So in Scala, we can do what we had on a previous slide.
So on the previous slide, we had this thing.
left. So you can do the result of the if then else is going to give you a value.
So here's Scala. So here in Scala, we have this. We have valy equals. Then we
we have this brace, which is perfectly valid syntax.
And then in here, we're going to set a var i,
we're going to set it equal to x,
we're going to set a var z equal to 0.
Then we're going to do this while.
So while i greater than 0, we're going to do this.
We're going to decrement i, and then increment z.
And then when we're done, we're going to return z.
And then that's what that last expression is going to get stored in y.
And that's perfectly valid.
If I try to do that kind of thing in Java or C,
notice I have int y equals and then miss brace.
If I try to do that the compiler will complain.
Loops and semicolons are not in the Java and C expression language.
So you have to have expressions with these to the right of the equal sign.
So how can we make it Java RC? Anybody have an idea? All that stuff in the braces, where would that go?
Think about it, if I wanted to write something like this in Java NC, what does it kind of look like?
Sort of put it in another function.
Put it in another function. Looks like another function. So that's the answer. We would have to move it.
So we would call it G maybe.
And so we would get this thing on the right.
There's our G. This is Java and C.
So you would implement G like this.
This is all the stuff that we had in those braces that didn't compile.
And now we would call G. We would call the function.
Okay.
You can also do that at Scala.
That's perfectly fine.
So you have this separate function G.
So functions are in the expression language of Scala, Java and C.
So if you think back to your experience in systems, you dealt with assembly language.
Assembly language consists of statements.
When we have a statement, we're doing something like move this data from, move this, maybe
So in here we're moving this value 5 to this location called EAX.
Move 6 into...
Or add, sorry, add 6 to what's in EAX, and then move, I forget which order, I don't do
assembly language.
So that's statements.
You're basically saying do something to the memory of the computer.
In expression, with expressions, there are much more abstract ways of expressing ideas
computation.
to saying add this to expression five plus six so I want you to evaluate that.
So imperative languages, Java and C for example, distinguish the statement
language from the expression language. Functional languages like Scala, Haskell,
OCaml, standard ML, tend to emphasize expressions and Scala has only
expressions so we don't we don't have statements in Scala.
So now we're starting to get into kind of the nitty-gritty technical details of programming
languages.
So don't get too scared.
We're going to cover some formal semantics here.
This is a preview of something you're going to see later this quarter.
We have formal semantics.
So a mathematical function takes arguments and gives results.
So if you think about a mathematical function like from high school algebra, you put in some input, you get out some output, an expression is going to be pure if that's all it does.
So if you think about, you've got some class in Java and you have a function and it's changing some instance variable, that's got a side effect.
So it's not a pure function or a pure.
The method isn't a pure function.
That's a little bit non-technical way to express that.
So a pure expression does not modify the store.
So here we have the store, I think that's a XI.
I always double check all my Greek letters before I do.
We'll do this another week, I think it's week four we do this.
But we're not changing the variable store so
you don't have to worry about this so much right now.
This thing on the right.
So, anything that's not pure is a side effect.
So assigning to a variable, changing of control with
like a go to and see doing any sort of IO, console, network, database IO, any of
that, file IO, that's a side effect. Here, if I have a side affecting expression
that modifies the store, that's what this example is. This thing's on the right
are the things that the labels. So this is like some sort of assignment here.
So expressions, we have the rules, boolean, character, integer, string.
Operators, arithmetic, bitwise, logical.
Or function calls, all those are expressions.
In Scala everything's an expression.
If I do this assignment, var y 0 and lx equals y is 5, what is the type and value of x?
So here the x is going to be an int value of 5.
Let's test it out.
R y equals zero.
Val x equals y equals five.
So yes, that's what I thought.
Notice how if I type y, y evaluates to five.
If I evaluate x, I get nothing.
Well, it's not really nothing.
nothing is something else. It's a unit. Why is that? So what happened here is that the
value of this expression here, because it's an assignment, is a unit. It's like a void.
And so in Java and C, if we do this, the value of X is going to be 5. That's because when
they created that language, they wanted the ability to initialize multiple variables to
the same value in one statement.
In Scala though, doing an assignment has value,
has a type unit.
So that whole expression evaluates to type unit,
even though it does something,
like stores the value in x,
that's a side effect.
In C,
So, this part before the semicolon is the expression.
This part with the whole expression plus the semicolon is a statement, that means do it.
It's like telling the compiler, I want you to create instructions to do the thing.
So you're giving a directive.
Return statements.
In C if I have return 1 plus x, this here is an expression.
But this whole thing is the statement, because of the separate form.
And the return keyword.
So in C we have selection statements, those are if then else, or switch case,
we're familiar with those in C.
And iteration statements, while, do while, and for, these are our loops,
This is why I don't use the word loop as much in Scala.
I like to say expressions for expressions.
This is why I kept saying.
So in C, we have this.
So you cannot use statements verbatim as part of expressions.
You use functions in these languages
to turn statements into expressions.
So that's why we had to move that thing out to a function.
So side-effecting expressions in C.
I have int x equals one and then I try to print.
After this plus plus business here, that's a pre-increment.
So it's going to increment x first, and then print two.
The value of x is now two, and that's a side effect.
You change something in memory.
Here if I have int x equals one, if I do that, and I try to print it,
it will print one and post increment.
But once this statement finishes, there is a side effect of x getting
incremented to two.
Next one, so x equals 1 plus y equals 5.
This is going to assign 5 to y.
And so then the whole value of, so in c, when you do this assignment,
the value of that expression is going to be 5.
And then we're going to say 1 plus 5, so x will get 6.
And the value of that whole expression is 6.
And even though we don't save it anywhere, it does evaluate to 6.
So this one here is a problem.
So if x equals 1, and then I have this business in here, so what am I doing?
I'm going to say x equals x plus 1, and then add x, and then print it.
There's no sequence point.
This is undefined.
So what's a sequence point?
Well, a sequence point is a point in the execution of a C program at which all previous side effects are guaranteed to be complete.
So in this case, we don't know.
The language doesn't define what the order is.
And so we don't know what happens.
And so in the C language, it might compile.
It might complain and not compile.
It depends on the compiler.
So side effects are very common in object-oriented programming.
Here, I have some, I think it's C++ or Java code,
it's probably Java code, it's probably Java code.
So here, I'm updating x, right?
I have this private in x, changing x to have x minus c.
If I do that, I had a side effect,
it changed something in memory.
Same with g with y.
So the results are often going to depend on the object state and
potentially on the entire execution history.
Cuz you don't know what it was called before, right?
.
So in c, if we wanna sequence expressions,
we can use this comma operator.
So if I have a statement sequence in c, this is what it looks like.
This is a statement in x equals 5.
x times equal 2.
Notice the semicolon, right?
So we have statement, statement, and then a printf expression
within a statement.
We can do an expression sequence this way with these commas.
Sorry, these commas here.
So here I have x times equal 2.
Now, that comma means that in the language,
this will happen before this gets passed and spliced in here at the printf.
This comma means that this defines the fact that this had to have,
the side effect has to have, executed and completed before this is accessed and used.
So here's our summary.
Statements are gonna change memory.
They are executed in sequence.
Expressions can be pure, and they can also side effect.
You can sequence by an operator in the expression language.
So in C, we have expression one comma expression two comma up to some other.
And we can do a conditional by operator in an expression language like this.
So you can see we have some expression here, question mark.
If that evaluates to true, we'll use this expression.
We'll evaluate this expression.
If this evaluates to false, we'll evaluate that expression.
And that is the end.
So I got through all 18 slides.
I was worried.
But that means that we should have covered everything you need for the homework and the
quiz for this week.
So feel free to call out questions in Discord as you go.
And there is one programming note.
The week of May, I believe it's May 12th.
So, a long time away, it's after the midterm, but on that week, we will have class remotely
that night.
I will be on business.
I'll be out of town.
I'll be in my hotel room, teaching from my laptop in the hotel room.
So, everybody will come to class on Zoom that night.
So, write it down now, put it in your calendar.
I'll send out a note about it, too.
It's a little ways away, but I have to go to some business meetings because we have
some big new projects coming, and I need to be at company headquarters for that.
So that's 13th, 13th, 12th.
So keep that in mind.
But like I said, I'll send that out the next few weeks.
OK.
Thanks.
Have a good week.
And Raven, did you want to hear your question?
I'm going to shut down the online meeting here, everybody's okay with that?
Have a good week.
Thank you, Jayden.
Have a good night.
Give me just a second.
Sorry.
.
Okay.
That's okay.
You don't always have the right language.
Yeah, but you're learning.
.
OK, so in Java, if you did this, are you specifically
asking about this class defined within the game?
So in Java, that would be a static class,
because it's defined in the object.
So like I said in class, anything that's in the object
corresponds to anything static in Java.
So that would be like a lot of times
because with the linguist we had static class node
that we were using.
Yeah, so that would be the same here,
so a shape is a static class defined within game of life.
Okay.
Yup.
So, it was a lot easier,
I just had to see it to understand
what you were getting at.
Yeah, I didn't know.
I knew what it was, but I don't know how to say it.
You weren't sure what words to use.
I don't know how to say it.
That's okay.
Have a good week.
Thank you.
OK.
All right.
Oh yeah, I need to post these examples.
Oh yeah, I'm going to post them on this one?
No, the website?
I'll put it on the website.
Yeah, I just got to go find a website.
It'll probably be tomorrow.
Are you finding it a little easier this time?
I mean, it's only the first assignment so far that we had to do, the first quizzes.
I didn't feel like I started struggling until we got to midterm.
That's where it was starting to take off.
Yeah.
Cover a lot of stuff.
All at once.
Yeah, it gets progressively more complicated as we go.
But the first few weeks, it felt extremely easy because you showed the JAPA code.
get started early that's what i would say you know you come to class tuesday but if you've got
time wednesday start like working through it it's my advice nope start doing that
i find you know i find that a lot of people uh it's it's always it's very funny like
every time i teach i do my flex day thing and it never fails the first week it's 20% of the
They're like, I need a flex tape, because nobody's figured out how to budget their time yet.
You know, it takes a little bit of time.
And then it does taper off, there's usually a few, but like the first couple weeks is
more and then people are starting to get used to how to budget their time anymore.
Yeah, exactly.
It takes time to figure it out.
Cool.
Alright.
So far not bad.
Good.
You really got me into using IntelliJ.
Oh good.
Oh, good.
I use it a lot more in the LS code.
Yeah, I got to start using the BS code more.
And I installed it on my work machine.
I installed it on my teaching machine last night, because I was, was it last night?
Or was it during the day?
I was trying to look at a markdown file and.
Oh, OK, yeah.
Yeah.
I wanted a markdown reader, and I was like, oh, it was last night I was preparing.
And I wanted to print.
But I wanted it to look like the markdown I did do that.
Makes sense.
Because when I took data structures,
my professors made us use Eclipse.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
And I did not like Eclipse.
I find Eclipse, I used to use Eclipse.
And it was fun to hear about.
Maybe it's not as bad anymore.
But the reason I switched to IntelliJ
was because I was doing Scala like, full time.
IntelliJ had better support from Scala.
I switched, and I never looked back.
That's how it tends to go.
I have a feeling I might switch to VS Code if I'm using Rust,
because VS Code is free,
and IntelliJ is free for Java or Scala,
but if you want to use a JetBrains product for Rust,
you have to pay for it.
Or you can use it for yourself, but I can't use it at work without a license, and they're
not going to want to pay for a license.
Yeah, of course.
Yep.
I had an issue with IntelliJ for something I was trying to do, and it wanted me to pay
for their thingy.
And I was like, no, I'm good.
Thank you, though.
I remember what I was trying to do on IntelliJ, and then I popped up.
All right.
Well, have a good week.
Yep.
You too.
If I have any questions, we'll let you know.
Please do.
Knees up!
Thank you.
Silence.
you
Thank you.
Okay.